Alright.
好的。
Um, I'd like to get started.
我准备开始了。
First, can anyone hear me?
首先，大家都能听到我说话吗？
Yes.
是的。
Good, thank you very much.
好的，非常感谢。
Alright, today I want to talk about,
好，今天我要讲的是，
the transition between running in user code,
在用户代码中运行程序
running programs in user code and executing in the kernel,
和在内核中执行之间的转换，
and this is the transition that has to happen
这就是必须要发生的转换，
whenever a program makes a system call
每当程序进行系统调用时，
where it experiences a fault like a page fault, a divide by zero
通过一个错误，比如页面错误，除零错误，
or if a device decides to interrupt
或者设备决定中断
and needs to be served by a kernel device driver.
并且由内核设备驱动程序提供服务。
There's a lot of careful design and some important details
这里面有很多精心的设计和一些重要的细节，
that go into how these traps, from user to kernel happen
深入了解这些 trap 是如何从用户到内核的，
and the details are pretty important
细节很重要，
for enforcing isolation security and also performance,
对于实施隔离安全和性能，
there's many programs that transition of the kernel a lot,
有很多程序进行了大量的内核转换，
either due to system calls a page page faults,
或者由于系统调用页面错误，
and it can be super important
它可以是非常重要的
that the trap mechanism is as [] as possible.
trap 机制尽可能地[]。
Alright, so starting situation is pretty familiar
好的，开始的情况是比较熟悉的，
where we have our user program,
我们有用户程序，
I use the shell as an example.
我使用 shell 作为示例。
Running in user space.
在用户空间中运行。
Um, we have a kernel,
嗯，我们有一个内核，
the shell would like to do make a system call into the kernel.
shell 希望进行系统调用进入内核。
And going to use write, use this shell writing its prompt
将使用 write ，使用 shell 输出其提示符，
the very first write that happens after you boot xv6,
引导 xv6 之后发生的第一次写入，
use the shell trying to write to make the write system calls an example.
使用 shell 用来写入的 write 系统调用作为示例。
And so we need to figure out
所以我们需要弄清楚，
how to actually get execution to transfer from running in the shell
如何真正从 shell 运行中转换，
and user space with user privileges,
具有用户权限的用户空间，
after running in the kernel supervisor privileges,
在内核中运行则具有管理员权限，
the state of the hardware is going to be very important,
硬件的状态将非常重要，
because a lot of what we're doing
因为我们所做的很多事情
is kind of changing the hardware state
都在某种程度上改变了硬件状态，
from state appropriate for running user code
从适合运行用户代码的状态
to a state appropriate for running kernel code.
到适合运行内核代码的状态。
The state that we care about,
我们所关心的状态，
the biggest state maybe the 32 user registers.
最重要的可能是 32 个用户寄存器。
As you remember this from monday's discussion,
你还记得周一的讨论中提到的这一点，
we have all the user registers seems like a0 and a1.
我们有所有的用户寄存器，比如 a0 和 a1 。
RISC-V has a whole lot of these 32 in total
RISC-V 总共有 32 个，
and we can expect user code to use all of them.
我们可以在用户代码使用它们。
It's going to get the highest performance if it uses all of them,
如果它们全部使用，将获得最高的性能，
many of them have special purposes,
它们中的许多有特殊的目的，
a few which we'll see a particularly interesting one is the stack pointer,
我们将看到的，特别有趣的一个是栈指针，
is actually one of these 32 general purpose registers.
实际上是这 32 个通用寄存器中的一个。
Okay, we have these registers including stack pointer,
好的，我们有这些寄存器，包括栈指针，
there's a separate program counter register in the hardware.
硬件中有单独的程序计数器寄存器。
There's the current mode either supervisor
当前模式可以是管理员模式，
or user and of course it's user mode.
当然也可以是用户模式。
We're executing up in the shell.
我们在 shell 里执行。
And then there's a bunch of registers special registers
然后是许多寄存器，特殊寄存器，
that control how the CPU works,
它们控制着 CPU 的工作方式，
like there's the satp register, that contains a pointer to the page table
比如 satp 寄存器，它包含指向页表的指针，
and it'll turn out there's a couple of others
还有其他几个
that are super important for this discussion,
对这场讨论非常重要，
there's stvec which is the address the instruction
有 stvec ，它是（处理中断）指令的地址，
that should handle traps in the kernel.
该指令处理内核中的 trap 。
There's a register called SEPC for saving the program counter during a trap
有一个名为 SEPC 的寄存器，用于在 trap 期间保存程序计数器，
and we'll see there's another one called sscratch is also very important,
还有一个叫 sscratch 的寄存器也很重要，
so this is the state of the running machine at the time of the system call
这是系统调用时正在运行的计算机的状态，
and we actually need to change a bunch of this state,
实际上我们需要改变这种状态，
or do things to the state as part of getting into the kernel,
或者作为进入内核的一部分对状态执行操作，
and setting ourself up to run just ordinary C functions in the kernel.
并设置为只在内核中运行普通的 C 函数。
Certainly at the instant of the trap,
当然在 trap 发生的时候，
all the state of the CPU is set up to run user code not not kernel code.
CPU 的所有状态都设置为运行用户代码，而不是内核代码。
So the things that are going to need to happen
因此，发生的事情
is kind of a preview of what I'll talk about,
在某种程度上是我将要谈论的内容的预览，
one is that, we need to save all 32 registers,
一个是，我们需要保存全部的 32 个寄存器，
because we want to resume the user code transparently,
因为我们希望透明地恢复用户代码，
particularly if there's a device interrupt which the user code isn't expecting
特别是在不是用户代码预期的设备中断的情况下，
and we want to be able to have the kernel serve the interrupt,
我们希望能够让内核为中断提供服务，
and then resume the user code without ever noticing any difference
然后恢复用户代码，而不会注意到任何差异，
and that means that these 32 registers can't be disturbed by the kernel,
这意味着这 32 个寄存器不能被内核干扰，
which since the kernel, you need to use the registers
从内核开始，你需要使用它拥有的寄存器
it has to save them all somewhere,
将它们全部保存在某个地方，
first these need to be saved.
首先，这些需要保存。
The program counter also needs to be saved somewhere,
程序计数器也需要保存在某个地方，
because we need a user, it's almost like a user register,
因为我们需要一个用户寄存器，
so, we need to continue executing the user program where it left off,
因此，我们需要在用户程序停止的地方继续执行，
we switch the mode to supervisor mode,
我们将模式切换到管理者模式，
because we need to use various privileges in the kernel.
因为我们需要使用内核中的各种权限。
Um just, page table pointer is currently pointing towards the user page table,
页表指针目前指向用户页表，
which only contains just the mapping is that user programs need.
它只包含用户程序需要的映射。
Plus one or two more as we'll see,
再加上一两个，我们会看到的，
but the user page table does not contain
但是用户页表不包含
the mappings for the bulk of the kernel data,
大量内核数据的映射，
so we need to switch page tables before we can run most kernel code.
因此，在运行大多数内核代码之前，我们需要切换页表。
We need to switch the stack pointer
我们需要将栈指针切换
to point to a stack that's in the kernel somewhere,
指向内核中某个位置的栈，
because we need to stack the call C functions on.
因为我们需要调用 C 函数使用的栈。
Um.
嗯。
And finally, we need to jump into,
最后，我们需要跳进，
once we've set all this up
一旦我们把这些都设置好了，
and switched all this all these resources
并将所有这些资源
to be appropriate for use in the kernel,
转换为适合在内核中使用的资源，
we need to jump to kernel C code,
我们需要跳到内核 C 代码，
and once we're in C code,
一旦我们进入 C 代码，
life is much more sort of business as usual,
事情就像往常一样，
we're just running C program in this kernel,
我们只是在内核中运行 C 程序，
and so far today at least,
至少到目前为止，
we'll talk about what the kernel does C code later,
我们稍后会讨论内核中 C 代码做了什么，
but today the discussion is really
但今天的讨论是
how to get from user space into the kernel into a position,
如何从用户空间进入内核，
where we can run C code in the kernel.
在那里我们可以在内核中运行 C 代码。
There's a couple of high-level goals,
有几个高层次的目标，
that constrain our design options for this,
这限制了我们在这方面的设计选择，
one is that for security and isolation,
一个是为了安全和隔离，
we really don't want to let
我们不想让
user code interfere with this user kernel transition,
用户代码干扰这个用户内核转换，
in a way that could be damaging to security
在某种程度上可能会破坏安全
and so that means that's
所以这意味着，
sort of hardware and kernel mechanisms that are involved in traps
trap 中涉及的各种硬件和内核机制，
really can't count on anything from user space,
不能指望任何来自用户空间的东西，
you know we can't assume anything about these registers,
我们不能对这些寄存器做任何假设，
they could be just filled with terribly malicious values,
它们可能包含恶意值，
so basically the xv6 trap handler
所以基本上 xv6 trap 处理程序
doesn't really even look at these registers just saves them away.
甚至不会真正查看这些寄存器，只是将它们保存起来。
Okay so we're going to want to be careful
好的，所以我们要小心，
to preserve isolation during this trap mechanism
在 trap 机制期间
against intentionally malicious user code
针对故意恶意的用户代码保持隔离，
and the other thing that's important is that,
另一件重要的事是，
we want to be transparent to user code,
我们希望这个对用户代码是透明的，
we'd like to be able to take the trap
我们希望能够处理 trap ，
and do our business in the kernel
并在内核中处理我们的事情，
and resume the user code
并恢复用户代码，
without it ever having to notice that anything funny happened.
而用户代码不会注意到发生了什么。
And that's just to make it easier to write user code.
这是为了让编写用户代码变得更容易。
And, something to note to,
而且，要注意的是，
we care about isolation security here,
我们这里关心的是隔离安全，
today we're just gonna talk about the.
今天我们想谈谈。
Those sort of aspects of security that involves getting into the kernel,
这些涉及进入内核的安全方面，
but of course this system called implementations,
当然，这个系统调用实现，
the actual write implementation in the kernel,
内核中实际的 write 实现，
also everything in the kernel has to be careful,
此外，内核中的所有内容都必须小心，
has to be written carefully and securely also,
也必须写得仔细和安全，
so even if this transition into the kernel is perfectly secure,
因此，即使这种向内核的转换是完全安全的，
the whole rest of the kernel has to be written securely
内核的其他部分都必须安全地编写，
and so mindful that user code may be trying to trick it.
而且要注意，用户代码可能会试图欺骗它。
A particularly important thing I want to talk about is
我想说的一件特别重要的事情是，
what it is that the mode flag controls,
模式标志控制的是什么，
this mode is either user or supervisor,
模式可以是用户模式或管理员模式，
of course user whatever user space
当然，用户可以使用任何用户空间，
and the mode flag is set to supervisor were executing in the kernel,
模式标志被设置管理员，则在内核中执行，
but it's important to know exactly what privileges we gain,
但重要的是要确切地知道我们获得了什么特权，
by changing the mode from user to supervisor,
通过将模式从用户改变为管理员，
and it turns out.
结果是。
These extra privileges are fairly restrictive,
这些额外的特权是相当有限的，
that is what you can do in supervisor mode,
这是你在管理员模式下可以做的，
you couldn't do in user mode,
在用户模式下不能做，
not maybe as a privilege as you might think so,
可能不是你想的那样的特权，
this is supervisor mode exactly what it controls.
这正是它所控制的管理员模式。
One thing it does is you can now read and write the control registers.
它所做的一件事是你可以读写控制寄存器。
And, that is, if your supervisor mode,
而且，如果你在管理员模式，
you can read and write satp, the page table pointer,
你可以读写 SATP ，即页表指针，
this stvec pointer which controls where traps going the kernel,
这个 stvec 指针，控制 trap 进入内核的位置，
This register that holds the save program counter during a trap
这个寄存器在 trap 期间保存程序计数器，
in sscratch register plus a few others,
到 sscatch 寄存器加某些值，
so supervisor could read and write these registers
因此管理员模式可以读写这些寄存器，
and user code could not.
而用户代码则不能。
The only other thing, supervisor code can do is,
另一件事，管理员模式代码可以做的是，
it can use ptes,
它可以使用 PTE ，
they have the pte_u flag set.
设置了 PTE_U 标志。
I don't know if you remember
我不知道你是否还记得，
but there's this pte_u flag be set or not set
但是在每个页表条目上都有
on each page table entry.
这个 PTE_U 标志被设置或不被设置。
A flag that has this,
带有此标志的，
sorry, sorry,
不好意思，
can use ptes.
可以使用 PTE 。
They don't have the pte_u flag set,
它们没有设置 PTE_U 标志，
if the pte_u flag is set,
如果 PTE_U 标志被设置，
it means that user code can use that page table entry,
这意味着用户代码可以使用该页表项，
if this flag isn't set in a page table entry,
如果在页表条目中没有设置该标志，
it means only supervisor mode can use it.
这意味着只有管理者模式才能使用它。
And you will see that's important a little bit,
你会发现这有点重要，
but, these are really the only things that supervisor mode can do
但是，这些确实是管理者模式唯一可以做的事情，
it can't do anything else in particular,
它不能特别做其他任何事情，
for example a supervisor mode code can't
例如，管理者模式代码不能
just read and write arbitrary addresses,
读写任意地址，
say physical addresses,
比如物理地址，
you know supervisor mode is forced to go through the page table
管理者模式被强制通过页表（访问内存），
just like any other code,
就像任何其他代码一样，
if a virtual address isn't in the page,
如果虚拟地址不在页面中，
isn't in the current page table pointed to by satp,
不在 satp 指向的当前页表中，
or if it has a pte_u bit flags set,
或者它设置了 PTE_U 标志，
which means it's the user pte,
这意味着它是用户 PTE ，
then supervisor mode cannot use that address,
则管理员模式不能使用该地址，
so we're even in supervisor mode were restricted to whatever virtual address,
所以我们在管理模式下也被限制到任何虚拟地址，
virtual addresses were set up on the current page table.
在当前页表上设置了虚拟地址。
And that's it, so we were just allowed to do these things,
就是这样，所以我们就被允许做这些事情，
so you know we'll see,
因此，我们将看到，
as a significant constraint on what the trap code can do.
trap 代码可以做什么，这是一个重要的约束。
When we're entering the kernel, can't do just anything,
当我们进入内核的时候，什么都不能做，
going to preview a bit,
预习一下，
I'm gonna spend most of this lecture in gdb,
这节课中，我将在 gdb 中花大部分时间，
actually tracing through the execution
跟踪整个执行过程
of a trap entry into the kernel in return,
内核中的 trap 条目的返回值，
this can be a lot of details in order to.
这里有很多细节，以便。
Um, maybe sort of help you, see head what's coming,
也许对你有点帮助，看看接下来会发生什么，
we're gonna be tracing a shell's call to a write,
我们将跟踪 shell 调用以进行写入，
which from the shell's point of view
从 shell 的角度来看，
is just a C function call as part of the shell,
只是作为 shell 的一部分的 C 函数调用，
in fact write makes this,
实际上 write 实现了这一点，
write issues a system call
write 会发出系统调用，
by issuing the ecall instruction,
通过发出 ecall 指令，
which switch is another kernel supervisor mode where that goes immediately,
直接跳转到内核管理者模式，
that is the very first instruction
这是第一条指令
is executed in the kernel and supervisor mode,
在内核和管理者模式中执行，
is a function written in assembler called uservec.
是用汇编语言编写的函数 uservec 。
And this is in the part of the trampoline,
这是 trampoline 的一部分，
in trampoline.S in the kernel source,
在内核代码的 trampoline.S 中，
so the very first code that's executed,
所以第一个被执行的代码，
this uservec assembler function.
是这个 uservec 汇编函数。
And next, that assembler function jumps into C code,
接下来，汇编函数跳转到 C 代码，
in particular a function called usertrap, in trap.c.
特别是 trap.c 中名为 usertrap 的函数。
And now we're getting into C code, so things are much easier to understand,
现在我们开始 C 代码，所以事情就容易理解了，
usertrap sees oh we're executing a system call,
usertrap 执行系统调用，
and it calls a function called syscall,
它调用一个名为 syscall 的函数。
which looks at the system call number in a table
它查看表中的系统调用号，
and calls the particular function inside the kernel
并调用内核内的特定函数，
that implements that system calling for us it's going to be write
它实现了调用我们系统，就是 write ，
and write does this business it happens,
write 来做这件事，
to arrange for whatever bytes were written to appear on the console
安排写入的任何字节显示在控制台上，
and when it's finished it returns back up to this system call function
并且当它完成时，返回到这个系统调用函数，
and then the system call function in order to return back to user space,
然后系统调用函数返回到用户空间，
because we want to resume.
因为我们想恢复。
After this ecall, there's a bunch of stuff,
在这个 ecall 之后，有很多东西，
we'll see, that has to happen.
是必须要发生的。
In order to return to user space,
为了返回用户空间，
there's a separate function called usertrapret,
有一个单独的函数 usertrapret ，
it's written in C, it's in trap.c,
它是用 C 写的，在 trap.c 中，
that does the part of this return to user space,
这一部分确实会返回到用户空间，
that's convenient to do in C code,
这在 C 代码中很方便，
there's some final things that really can only be done in assembly code,
有一些最后的事情只能在汇编代码中完成，
the code for that is during an assembler
这方面的代码是在汇编程序期间编写的，
and again in this trampoline page in a function called userret.
在这个 trampoline 页面中，有一个名为 userret 的函数。
The last last assembly stuff has to happen
最后的汇编工作，
and finally, this assembly function issues,
最后这个汇编函数执行，
the machine instruction that returns back in user space
机器指令返回到用户空间，
and resume execution after the ecall.
并在 ecall 之后恢复执行。
Right, does anybody want to ask a question,
好的，有没有什么问题，
I'm about just switch into looking stuff with gdb,
我要换成用 gdb 查看代码，
any questions about the sort of high-level picture?
关于高层次图示有什么问题吗？
Alright I am going to.
好的，我要进行。
Sorry I can't.
对不起，我听不清。
Um, let me see what mode are vm.c functions running?
嗯，我想一下， vm.c 函数是在什么模式下运行？
vm.c functions, everything in there is part of the kernel,
vm.c 中的函数，其中的所有内容都是内核的一部分，
and it's running supervisor mode.
它运行在管理者模式。
Got it.
明白了。
Yeah.
好的。
OK, somebody asked why these functions are named this way?
好的，有人问为什么这些函数要这样命名？
Um.
嗯。
The naming is a bit of a disaster
命名有点灾难，
and for next year, I'm resolved to make them more rational.
明年我决定让它们变得更好理解。
I think the naming question might have referred to the name of the registers
我想命名问题可能与寄存器的名称有关，
in the previous board.
在前一块页上显示的寄存器。
They all start s for supervisor.
管理者模式都是以 s 开头。
Other than it, there's five people pick these names.
另外，有五个人选了这些名字。
Somebody's asking don't vm.c functions access physical memory directly?
有人问 vm.c 函数不是直接访问物理内存吗？
That's absolutely true,
这是绝对正确的，
the reason why they're allowed to do that
它们被允许这样做的原因是，
though is that the kernel carefully sets up direct mapping's in the page table,
内核在页表中精心设置了直接的映射，
there's been many many ptes in the page table,
页表中有很多 PTE ，
which cause, whenever the kernel tries to read or write a physical address,
这导致每当内核试图读取或写入物理地址时，
it actually is a virtual address that's translated by the kernel page table
它实际上是由内核页表转换的虚拟地址
and is a physical address that's equal to the virtual address who was issued.
并且是与发出的虚拟地址相等的物理地址。
So it's like super convenient in the kernel,
所以这在内核中非常方便，
what once you're using the kernel page table,
一旦你使用内核页表，
this kernel has all these direct mappings,
这个内核有所有这些直接映射，
but until we've set up,
但在我们准备好之前，
the current until the trap machinery has switched to the kernel page table,
当前直到 trap 机制切换到内核页表，
none of those mappings are available
这些映射都不可用，
until the kernel trap code is switched to the kernel page table,
在内核 trap 代码切换到内核页表之前，
we're still using the user page table
我们仍在使用用户页表，
which has none of these convenient mappings for physical addresses.
对于物理地址，它没有这些方便的映射。
Okay.
好的。
Can I ask a question?
我可以问个问题吗？
Please.
请问。
Um, so, I don't know this is maybe not exactly relevant to what was just said,
嗯，我不知道这可能跟刚才说的不太相关，
but um, the read and write system calls
但是，读写系统调用，
right like those are pretty expensive compared to just the memory store,
与内存存储相比是相当昂贵的，
because you have to actually switch mode and go back and forth,
因为你必须实际切换模式并来回切换，
would it be possible to just like,
有没有可能就像，
instead of when when you open a file instead of getting back a file descriptor,
当你打开文件时不是取回文件描述符，
that you call with a system call to get a page table mapping,
而是可以使用系统调用来调用它来获取页表映射，
and then you would just write to a certain address,
然后你只需写到某个地址，
that's just mapped to the device,
刚刚映射到设备的（的地址），
and you can set up the restrictions,
你可以设置这些限制，
so that the program can only write to a, to like a file descriptor
这样程序就只能写入，就像文件描述符一样，
that it's allowed to which is allowed to through the virtual page table mapping,
它被允许通过虚拟页表映射，
instead of jumping to the kernel back.
而不是跳回内核。
Yeah that's a good observation
是的，这是一个很好的观察，
and indeed many operating systems provide this
事实上，许多操作系统都提供
what's called memory mapped file access,
这种所谓的内存映射文件访问，
where indeed the map pages that correspond to the file contents
其中与文件内容相对应的映射页，
into the into your virtual into user virtual address space,
进入用户虚拟地址空间，
so you can read or write them directly through memory,
所以你可以直接通过内存读取或写入它们，
in fact you'll be implementing a version of this
事实上，你将在几周内的
in the mmap lab, in a couple of weeks.
mmap 实验中实现此版本。
And indeed as you imply it's a good deal faster,
事实上，正如你所说的那样，它要快得多，
for many programs that calling read and write.
对于许多程序的调用读取和写入。
Okay.
好的。
I am switch to the gdb world.
我要切换到 gdb 了。
Alright, at this point, everybody should, um,
好的，现在大家都应该，
see my screen share.
能看到我的屏幕共享。
Um.
嗯。
We're going to watch an xv6 system called the write.
我们将查看 xv6 系统的 write 。
The shell's write of its initial prompt,
shell 对其初始提示符的写入，
make its way through the system,
在系统中使用的方式，
you can see the user code that initiates this in sh.c.
你可以在 sh.c 中看到发起此操作的用户代码。
I'm sure that was just making the write system call,
我确信在进行 write 系统调用，
with this dollar sign, prompt we fire up gdb.
使用美元符号，提示我们启动 gdb 。
Excellent, so what actually happens when user code when the shell calls write,
太好了，那么当用户代码在 shell 调用 write 时实际发生了什么呢？
write is just a it's a library function
write 只是一个库函数，
that's part of the, that's linked into the shell,
是一部分，连接到 shell ，
and you can see the source for it in usys.S.
你可以在 usys.S 中看到它的源码。
So it's this couple of instructions,
就是这些指令，
here's the implementation of the write function,
这是 write 函数的实现，
that the shell is actually calling,
shell 实际上调用的，
and this is a very short function,
这是一个非常短的函数，
all it's doing is loading into a7 a number SYS_write,
它所做的就是将一个数字 SYS_write 加载到 a7 中，
it's just symbolically defined to be sixteen that tells the kernel,
它定义为 16 ，这告诉内核，
I want to run the sixteenth system call which happens to be write.
我想运行第 16 个系统调用，就是 write 。
And then this little function uses the ecall instruction,
然后这个函数使用 ecall 指令，
which is what actually gets the code into the kernel,
实际上就是将代码转入内核，
the kernel does this thing and then when the kernel can be done,
内核做这件事，然后当内核完成时，
it returns back into user space to execute the instruction after the ecall,
它返回到用户空间，执行 ecall 之后的指令，
which is that write that returns back to the shell,
这里是返回到 shell 的 write 操作，
returns from that write library function back into the shell.
从 write 库函数返回到 shell 中。
So what I'd like to do
所以我想要做的
in order to show the system call part of this,
是展示系统调用的一部分，
I'm going to start by putting a break point on that ecall instruction,
我将首先在 ecall 指令上设置一个断点，
and we need to know its address, of course,
我们当然需要知道它的地址，
but we can find that out by looking in sh.asm,
我们可以通过查看 sh.asm 找到，
which xv6 compilation process produces,
是 xv6 编译过程产生的，
sh.asm, there's assembly code
sh.asm 是汇编代码，
with addresses of the, the instructions for the shell,
包含 shell 指令地址，
I'm going to put a break point on the ecall instruction,
我将在 ecall 指令上设置一个断点，
which is d address de6.
即地址 0xde6 。
Actually, I'm gonna actually start xv6 running,
我要开始运行 xv6 ，
and I'm hoping to have the system break in the shell
我希望让系统在 shell 中断，
just before executing ecall.
在执行 ecall 之前。
Alright, excellent, now, you can see from gdb,
好的，太好了，现在你可以从 gdb 上看到，
we're about to about to execute that ecall.
我们即将执行那个 ecall 。
Let's just check, there we are where we think we are,
让我们检查一下，我们是不是在想的那里，
print, we can print the program counter,
打印，我们可以打印程序计数器，
0xde6 just what we asked for.
就是我们设置断点的 0xde6 。
Um, we can also print the all 32 registers,
我们也可以把所有的 32 个寄存器打印出来。
and some of these values
其中一些值，
whatever we don't know we don't care what they are,
我们不知道，也不关心它们是什么，
but a0 a1 and a2 are the three arguments that the shell passed write,
但是 a0 a1 和 a2 是 shell 传递给 write 的三个参数，
so those arguments are
所以这些参数是，
a file descriptor two in a0,
a0 中的文件描述符 2 ，
the pointer to the buffer of characters the shell wants to write in a1
a1 中指向 shell 要写入的字符缓冲区的指针，
and the number of characters it wants to write in a2.
以及 a2 中它要写入的字符数。
And we can convince ourselves
我们可以确信，
that we're looking at a code we think we're looking at,
查看的代码就是我们想要看的。
by actually printing out the bytes in that buffer, the shell wants to write
通过打印 shell 要写入的缓冲区中的字节，
and indeed, it's a dollar sign and a space,
事实上，这是一个美元符号和一个空格，
so, we're at the system call that we, we hope to be at.
所以，我们在我们希望在的系统调用。
One thing to notice is
需要注意的一件事是
that the program counter and stack pointer both at low addresses,
程序计数器和堆栈指针都在低地址，
addresses quite close to zero,
地址非常接近于零，
and just reinforces our belief,
这强化了我们的信念，
that we're still executing in user
我们仍然在用户地址运行，
and the user address space where all the addresses are quite small,
用户地址空间中的地址都很小，
once we get to the kernel's, see the addresses are,
一旦我们到达内核，就会看到地址是，
the kernel is actually loaded much much higher in memory.
内核在内存中的要高得多。
Okay, we, the point of the system calls to switch around a lot of state,
好的，系统调用的要点是要切换很多状态，
one of the most important pieces of state that has to get switched
必须切换的最重要的状态之一
and we have to live with before it's switched is the current page table,
在它被切换之前，我们不得不使用当前的页表。
of course we can look at satp.
我们可以查看 satp 。
But all we get there is the address in physical memory page tables,
但是我们在那里得到的只是物理内存页表中的地址，
doesn't actually tell us much about
并没有告诉我们
what the mappings are with the page table looks like,
页表的映射是什么样子，
luckily there's a way in QEMU ask it to print the current page table
幸好 QEMU 有办法打印当前页表，
and if I print control-a c, I get into the QEMU monitor or console,
如果我按下 control-a c ，我进入 QEMU 监视器或控制台，
and if I then type info mem, it'll print the complete page table,
如果我输入 info mem ，它会打印完整的页表，
this is a very small page table
{}这是一个非常小的页表，
that contains only six mappings,
只包含 6 个映射，
of course it's the page table for the shell.
当然这是 shell 的页表。
Shell's a pretty small program
Shell 是一个相当小的程序，
and these six mappings are in order the shell's instructions,
这 6 个映射是按 shell 指令的顺序排列的，
the shell's data, an invalid page which access the stack guard page,
shell 的数据，访问栈保护页的无效页，
in case the shell tries to use too much stack space
以防 shell 试图使用过多的栈空间，
and we can see it's invalid
我们可以看到它是无效的，
because it doesn't have the u flag set,
因为它没有设置 U 标志，
over here, in this attribute or flag column,
在这里，在属性或标志列中，
these are all the pte underscore flags r w and x,
这些都是 PTE 下划线标志 r w 和 x ，
are just control whether a pte can be read or written or executed,
控制 PTE 是否可以读、写或执行，
the next column is u,
下一列是 u ，
and that's whether or not the pte_u flag is set
这就是是否设置了 PTE_U 标志
and user code can only get at pte entries for which the u flag is set,
并且用户代码只能使用设置了 U 标志的 PTE 条目，
I don't know what the next column is, I have to admit,
我不知道下一栏是什么，我得承认，
and the next column is a,
再下一栏是 a ，
for whether the pte entries ever been used
表示 PTE 条目是否使用过，
and d for whether a write has ever been issued for this address.
以及 d 表示是否曾经对该地址写入。
Okay, so we have this tiny page table,
好的，那么我们有这个小的页表，
in the last two page table entries by the way,
顺便说一下，在最后两个页表条目中，
are way up at an enormous virtual addresses,
都位于一个很大的虚拟地址上，
close to the very close to the top of the virtual address space
非常接近虚拟地址空间的顶部，
and this is these two as you read about in the book,
这就是你们在书中读到的这两个，
I will hear much more about the trapframe page
我会听到更多关于 trapframe 的页面，
and now the trampoline page,
这个是 trampoline 页面，
as you can see neither of them has the u bit set,
你可以看到，它们都没有设置 u 标志，
so user code can't get at either of these can use either of these addresses,
所以用户代码不能访问这两个地址中的任何一个，
but once we enter supervisor mode, we can get at these two pages.
但是一旦我们进入管理者模式，我们就可以进入这两个页面。
Alright.
好的。
Um, one thing this notice about
嗯，有一点需要注意，
this page table is there's no mapping for anything in the kernel,
这个页表没有内核中的任何东西的映射，
there's no physical address mapping,
没有物理地址映射，
there's no mapping for the kernel's data,
没有内核数据映射，
the kernel's instructions or anything else,
内核指令或其他任何东西，
this is accepted the last just the very last two pages,
这只接受最后两页，
now, this is the page table almost entirely dedicated to user execution
现在，这是几乎完全专用于用户执行的页表，
and is not directly particularly useful for executing the kernel.
并且对于执行内核并不特别有用。
All right what's the what's the attribute
好的，在页表顶部
on the on the page table listing on the top?
列出的属性是什么？
I believe this means the page tables ever been,
我相信这意味着页表曾经，
this page table entry has ever been accessed by code,
该页表项曾经被代码访问过，
that is, whether it's ever issued an address
就是有没有访问地址
that refers to the page table.
到这个页表。
And the d is whether the programs ever written.
d 是程序是否曾经写过。
They've done a store through this page table entry
他们已经通过这个页表条目进行了存储，
and these are this the hardware maintains
这些都是硬件
for the convenience of the operating system
为了操作系统的方便而维护的，
and operating systems more sophisticated than xv6.
以及比 xv6 更复杂的操作系统。
We need to evict pages if they're running short on physical memory,
如果页面的物理内存不足，我们需要将其逐出，
they may need to write some pages of memory to disk,
它们可能需要将一些内存页面写入磁盘，
and invalidate the page entries to free up the physical memory,
并使页面条目无效以释放物理内存，
and many policies,
很多策略，
you can imagine a operating system using the [pic] which pages to exist,
你可以想象一个操作系统使用的 pic 页面存在，
now we'll consult the bits to see
现在我们查看比特，
whether this page table entry has ever even been used
看看这个页表条目是否曾经被使用过，
and it hasn't been used or have been used recently
它最近还没有用过或者已经用过了，
then that's a good candidate for evicting to disk.
那么这是一个很好的驱逐到磁盘的候选对象。
And d tells the kernel
d 告诉内核
that oh this page has actually been written since it was read from disk,
这一页实际上是从磁盘读取后写入的，
xv6 doesn't actually use either of these.
xv6 实际上并不使用这些标志。
Alright, other questions?
好的，还有其他问题吗？
Alright, let's execute the um.
好的，我们来执行这个。
Let me just remind us where we are going to print out the contents of the write,
我来提醒一下，我们将在哪里打印出 write 的内容，
we're in the write library function, in a, in the shell,
我们在 write 库函数，在一个 shell 中，
and the program counter is pointed to the ecall instruction,
并且程序计数器指向 ecall 指令，
we're about to execute the ecall instruction,
我们即将执行 ecall 指令，
still in user space but won't be for long.
仍在用户空间，但不会持续很长时间。
I executed the ecall instruction,
我执行了 ecall 指令，
okay so first question is where are we.
好的，那么第一个问题是我们在哪里。
After the ecall, we can look at the program counter.
在 ecall 之后，我们可以查看程序计数器。
We see this now used to be a very low number d
我们看到，现在这是一个非常低的数字 d6 ，
that's very high number,
那是非常高的数字，
in fact we look at the program counter is a virtual address
事实上，我们看到程序计数器是一个虚拟地址，
like all addresses that instructions use.
就像指令使用的所有地址一样。
And we can look at the page table,
我们可以看看页表，
actually let's just check what the page table is just to be sure,
实际上，为了确保正确，让我们检查一下页表，
I'm gonna ask you QEMU for info mem again,
我再次对 QEMU 输入 info mem ，
it's the very same page table,
这是完全相同的页表，
nothing's changed there,
那里什么都没变，
we'll look up our new current program counter,
我们将查找新的当前程序计数器，
there are the program counter
程序计数器
is at the right at the beginning of this trampoline page,
在这个 trampoline 页面开头处，
this mapped a way up high in the user memory.
这在用户内存中映射了高地址。
That's were executing, we can see the instructions that are there,
这是正在执行的，我们可以看到指令在那里，
I'm going to use.
那些我要用的指令。
Um.
嗯。
These are the instructions,
这些都是指令，
the very first instructions that the kernel executes in supervisor mode
内核在管理者模式下执行的第一条指令，
at the beginning very beginning of a trap
在 trap 刚开始的时候，
and threw some weirdness in gdb,
并在 gdb 中抛出了一些奇怪的东西，
we've actually already executed, the first instruction,
我们实际上已经执行了第一条指令，
at the very beginning of this page.
在本页的开头。
And we're about to execute the second instruction.
我们即将执行第二条指令。
We can look at the registers.
我们可以看看寄存器。
I don't know if you remember these register values but nothing has changed here,
我不知道你是否还记得这些寄存器值，但是这里什么都没有改变，
these are exactly the same register contents that the user program has,
这些与用户程序具有的寄存器内容完全相同，
so these are all full of user values for many of them
所以这些都充满了用户的值，对他们中的许多人来说
are all of them for all we know they're the only locations value exists,
就我们所知它们都是唯一值存在的地方，
so we have to be very careful
因此，我们必须非常小心，
when we can't actually use any registers at this point,
在这一点上不能实际使用任何寄存器，
without first saving those registers somewhere so we can restore them,
如果没有先将这些寄存器保存在某个地方以便我们可以恢复它们，
because if the kernel was to use
因为如果内核在此时
any of these registers at this point it would overwrite.
使用这些寄存器中的任何一个，它将被重写。
Um, whatever the user value is
不管用户值是多少，
and then if we tried to resume the user program,
然后如果我们试图恢复用户程序，
we wouldn't be able to set up its registers with the correct values
我们就不能用正确的值设置它的寄存器，
and the user program or just do something totally wrong.
用户程序会做一些完全错误的事情。
Question?
有问题吗？
Yes.
是。
Could you return to the instructions panel that you had before,
您能回到之前看到的说明面板上吗？
I'm wondering what the csrrw instruction is doing.
我想知道 csrrw 指令在做什么。
The csrrw,
csrrw ，
OK we'll talk about this, in a few minutes,
好的，我们几分钟后会谈到，
but the answer to your question is
但你问题的答案是，
that instruction swaps a0 with the contents of the special scratch register.
该指令将 a0 与特殊临时寄存器的内容交换。
Um, and so in yeah yeah, this is like super important.
所以是的，这是很重要的。
And basically answers the question
基本上回答了这样一个问题，
how can the this kernel trap code do anything if it can't use any registers,
如果内核 trap 代码不能使用任何寄存器，它怎么能做任何事情，
the answer that question is that exec- really has to execute this,
这个问题的答案是，出口确实必须执行这个，
csrrw a0 sscratch instruction,
csrrw a0 sscratch 指令，
that simultaneously saves a0 when scratch
这在 scratch 时保存 a0 ，
and happens to load scratch into a0.
并且将 scratch 加载到 a0 中。
So now the kernel can use a0 for whatever it wants to after this instruction.
因此，现在内核可以在此指令之后使用 a0 进行任何操作。
Okay, Thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Yeah.
好的。
Okay so we're currently this addresses 0x3ffffff000,
好的，我们目前的地址是 0x3ffffff000 ，
now this last page is the trampoline page
现在这最后一个页面是 trampoline 页面，
and we're currently executing in the trampoline page
我们目前正在 trampoline 页面中执行，
which contains the very first instructions of the kernel's trap handling code.
它包含内核 trap 处理代码的第一条指令。
Ecall doesn't switch page tables that's a very important thing about ecall
ecall 不会切换页表，这是 ecall 非常重要的一点，
and what that means is that these very first instructions
这意味着这些最早的指令
have to be present in every user page table.
必须出现在每个用户页表中。
Because ecall doesn't switch page tables,
因为 ecall 不切换页表，
we need to be executing the first bit of the kernel
我们需要执行内核的第一位，
somewhere in the user page table
在用户页表中的某个位置，
and it's this trampoline page
这个 trampoline 页面，
which the kernel carefully maps into every user page table
内核仔细地映射到每个用户页表中，
that gives the kernel a place to execute at the very beginning of a trap
这为内核提供了在 trap 开始时执行的位置，
when we're still using the user page table
当我们仍在使用用户页表时，
and the way this is controlled is through the stvec register,
其控制方式是通过 stvec 寄存器，
this is another privileged register
这是另一个特权寄存器，
only readable by the writable by the supervisor
仅管理者模式可读写，
and the kernel before it entered user space set up the stvec
内核在进入用户空间之前设置 stvec ，
to point to the place where the kernel wanted traps to go.
指向内核希望 trap 放置的位置。
And so as you can see the kernel
所以你可以看到内核，
has previously set up this stvec to this 0x3ffffff000 address
之前已将 stvec 设置为 0x3ffffff000 地址，
which is the beginning of the trampoline page.
这是 trampoline 页面的开始。
And it's this stvec register
就是这个 stvec 寄存器，
that its content is the reason why after the ecall,
它的内容就是为什么在 ecall 之后，
we ended up executing at this particular place.
我们最终在这个特定的地方执行。
And finally I just want to remind you that
最后我只想提醒你们，
even though the trampoline and trapframe pages
即使 trampoline 和 trap 帧页面
are mapped into the user page table user address space,
被映射到用户页表用户地址空间，
the user code cannot write them,
用户代码也不能写入它们，
because the ptes for them don't have the pte_u flag,
因为它们的 PTE 没有 u 标志，
so they're protected against user code.
因此，它们受到保护，不受用户代码的影响。
And that's why this trick is a part of the reason why this trick is safe.
这就是为什么这个小技巧是安全的原因。
I've been sort of telling you in assuming
我一直在告诉你，假设
that we're in supervisor mode,
我们处于管理者模式，
I don't know any way of finding out what mode the machine is in directly,
我不知道有什么方法可以直接找出机器处于什么模式，
but I do observe that the program counter is currently executing in a page,
但我确实观察到程序计数器当前在页面中执行，
the trampoline page that doesn't have a pte_u flag set
没有设置 PTE_U 标志的 trampoline 页面，
and that can only happen without a crash, if we are in supervisor mode,
这只能在没有崩溃的情况下发生，如果我们处于管理者模式，
so I deduce from the lack of a crash and the value of the program counter
所以我从没有崩溃以及程序计数器值推断，
that we must be in supervisor mode.
我们肯定处于管理者模式。
How we got here, of course I through ecall,
我们是怎么走到这的，当然是通过 ecall ，
ecall really just changes three things.
ecall 实际上改变了三件事。
First, ecall changes mode from user to supervisor,
首先， ecall 将模式从用户模式更改为管理者模式，
second ecall saves the program counter register in the sepc register,
第二， ecall 将程序计数器寄存器保存在 sepc 寄存器中，
so we can see the effect of that.
所以我们可以看到它的效果。
I think the program registers program counter,
我想程序计数器，
it's certainly no longer the user program counter,
它当然不再是用户程序计数器，
even though while the other registers were,
即使当其他寄存器在，
this, this value copied from stvec.
这个值是从 stvec 复制过来的。
And we can also print, the saved,
我们还可以打印，保存的，
it's the supervisor exception program counter what that stands for,
这是管理者模式例外程序的计数器，
but this is where ecall saves the user program, program counter,
但这是 ecall 保存用户程序计数器，
and that has a familiar value 0xde6
它具有熟悉的值 0xde6 ，
which is the address in user space of the ecall instruction.
该地址是 ecall 指令在用户空间中的地址。
So we got that one register at least saved away by ecall.
所以我们至少有一个寄存器被 ecall 存起来了。
And the final thing that ecall does the third thing,
最后一件事， ecall 做的第三件事，
it does is jump to the instruction that stvec points to.
它跳转到 stvec 指向的指令。
Alright, um.
好的，嗯。
So what needs to happen now,
所以现在需要做的是，
ecall down a little bit of work for us,
ecall 为我们做了点工作，
but it turns out we are nowhere near ready
但事实证明，我们还远没有准备好
to actually execute ordinary C code in the kernel,
在内核中执行普通的 C 代码，
what has to happen now do we need to save the 32 user register contents,
现在要做的是我们需要保存 32 个用户寄存器内容，
so we can later restore them
这样我们以后就可以恢复它们，
and when we want to resume the user code,
当我们想恢复用户代码时，
now we need to switch to the kernel page table,
现在我们需要切换到内核页表，
because currently we use the user page table,
因为目前我们使用的是用户页表，
we need to create a stack or find a stack
我们需要创建栈或查找栈，
and set the stack pointer register to point to the kernel stack,
并将栈指针寄存器设置为指向内核栈，
so we can run the C code which requires a stack
让我们可以运行需要栈的 C 代码，
and then we need to actually jump to
然后，我们需要跳转到
some sensible place in the C code in the kernel.
内核中 C 代码的某个合理位置。
Now as an aside,
现在顺便说一句，
you know ecall didn't do any of these things for us.
ecall 没有为我们做任何这些事情。
You know, but you could have the hardware
但是你可以让硬件
could have defined ecall to do much more.
定义 ecall 来做更多事情。
Many more of these steps for us instead of leaving them to software
对于我们来说，这些步骤要多得多，而不是把它们留给软件，
and as we'll see the during the software, it's not particularly straightforward,
正如我们将在软件过程中看到的，这并不是特别简单，
so you should ask yourself why the ecall doesn't do more of the work
所以你应该问问你自己，为什么 ecall 不能做更多的工作，
of getting from user space into the kernel,
从用户空间进入内核，
you know why doesn't it save their user registers
为什么不保存它们的用户寄存器，
or switch page table pointers to point to the kernel page table
或者切换页表指针指向内核页表，
or automatically set the stack pointer to point to the kernel stack,
或者自动将栈指针设置为指向内核栈，
or jump right to kernel C code []
或者直接跳转到内核 C 代码，
rather than having to go through all this complicated assembly code.
而不必经历所有这些复杂的汇编代码。
And there's actually been machines that have done all of these things,
实际上已经有机器完成了所有这些事情，
in hardware during system calls,
在系统调用期间的硬件中实现，
the RISC-V doesn't do any of them,
RISC-V 不会做任何一件事，
RISC-V really the attitude they've taken is
RISC-V 实际上采取的态度是，
the ecall does the absolute minimum that's required that it could possibly do
ecall 做了它可能做的最低要求，
and leave everything else up to software.
而把其他的一切都留给软件。
And the reason for this is
这样做的原因是，
because the RISC-V designers want to allow maximum flexibility to the software,
因为 RISC-V 设计者希望允许软件具有最大的灵活性，
the operating system programmers
操作系统程序员
to design the program operating system, however they like.
可以随心所欲地设计程序操作系统。
And so you can imagine ways xv6 really doesn't use this freedom,
所以虽然 xv6 没有使用这种自由的方式，
but other operating systems do,
但是其他操作系统是这样做的，
so some examples of things that are kind of enabled for the software to do,
我们可以举几个软件可以做的事情的例子，
because ecall so simple,
因为 ecall 太简单了，
Um.
嗯。
Maybe some operating systems can execute
也许一些操作系统可以执行，
some trap some system calls without switching page tables,
在不切换页表的情况下执行 trap 或系统调用，
the searching page page tables, expensive if ecall forces you to do it,
搜索页面表，如果 ecall 强迫你这样做的话会很昂贵，
now that rules out the possibility of very streamlined,
现在这就排除了非常精简的可能性，
implementations for some system calls that don't switch page tables.
一些不切换页表的系统调用的实现。
Um, some operating systems both user and kernel virtual addresses
有些操作系统既有用户虚拟地址，也有内核虚拟地址，
into a single page table
放入单个页表中，
and use the same page table for both user and kernel
并对用户和内核使用相同的页表，
and therefore don't even have to switch page tables
因此甚至不必切换页表，
ever when transitioning between user and kernel,
当在用户和内核之间转换时，
and for them also if you call switch page tables
对于它们，如果你调用交换页表，
would just be a waste and slow things down.
只会是一种浪费，让事情慢下来。
Maybe in some circumstances, system calls for example,
可能在某些情况下，比如系统调用，
some registers don't have to be saved
某些寄存器不需要保存，
and which ones have to be saved,
以及哪些必须被保存，
it depends on the software or the language and the compiler
这取决于软件或语言和编译器，
but might be able to save a lot of time by saving fewer than 32 registers,
但是可以通过少于 32 个寄存器来节省大量时间，
so you don't want ecall to kind of force you,
所以你不想让 ecall 强迫你，
you don't necessarily want ecall to force you to save all the registers.
你不一定希望 ecall 强制保存所有寄存器。
And finally, maybe no stack at all is required for some simple system calls,
最后，一些简单的系统调用可能根本不需要栈，
so again operating systems that care a lot about performance,
所以再说一次，操作系统非常关心性能，
it's good, the ecall doesn't force any particular stack policy on you.
这很好， ecall 不会将任何特定的栈策略强加给你。
And again there's many clever hardware, software schemes
再说一遍，有很多聪明的硬件或软件方案，
for very streamlined high performance system calls and tracks
用于非常精简的高性能系统调用和跟踪，
just because the performance of this stuff is super important
因为这个东西的性能是非常重要的，
and people worry about it a lot.
人们对此非常关心。
Okay, so back to xv6 and RISC-V.
好的，那么回到 xv6 和 RISC-V 。
The first thing we need to do is save some registers,
我们首先要做的是保存一些寄存器，
we can do hardly anything on the RISC-V without a few registers,
如果没有寄存器，我们几乎不能在 RISC-V 上做任何事情，
without being able to use registers,
在不能使用寄存器的情况下，
so what are options for saving user registers.
那么，保存用户寄存器的选项有哪些呢？
In on some other machine, we might be able to
在其他机器上，我们也许可以，
just write the contents of the 32 registers
只需将 32 个寄存器的内容
somewhere convenient in physical memory.
写入物理内存中方便的位置即可。
We cant actually really do that on the RISC-V
我们不能在 RISC-V 上真正做到这一点，
because supervisor code isn't allowed to directly access physical memory,
因为管理者代码不允许直接访问物理内存，
we can only use what's in the page table,
我们只能使用页表中的内容，
there's not much in the page table.
页表中的内容不多。
Another possibility that xv6 doesn't do is
xv6 做不到的另一种可能性是，
simply setting the satp to the kernel page table
只需将 satp 设置为内核页表，
and then we could use all the kernel mappings
然后我们可以使用所有内核映射，
and use them maybe to help us save the user registers
或许可以用它们来帮助我们保存用户寄存器，
and that be legal, the supervisor can certainly change satp.
而且这是合法的，管理者模式当然可以修改 satp 。
However, at this point in the trap handler namely at the beginning,
然而，在 trap 处理程序中的这一点，即在开始处，
we don't even know the address of the kernel page table,
我们甚至不知道内核页表的地址，
and furthermore the instruction that you execute to change satp
以及执行修改 satp 的指令，
require that the address that you're loading into satp come from a register,
要求从寄存器加载到 satp 的地址，
so we even execute the instruction to change page tables,
所以我们甚至执行指令来改变页表，
we need some spare registers
我们需要一些备用寄存器，
in order to put the new page table address in those registers,
以便将新的页表地址放入这些寄存器中，
so we can execute the satp modifying instruction.
因此，我们可以执行 satp 修改指令。
Alright, so we really need to save the user registers,
好的，我们需要保存用户寄存器，
there's two parts to the solution for how xv6 does this on the RISC-V.
对于 xv6 如何在 RISC-V 上执行此操作，解决方案分为两个部分。
One is part of the solution is that,
一个是解决方案的一部分，
xv6 into every user address, every user page table maps,
xv6 到每个用户地址，每个用户页表映射，
this trapframe page and every processes has its own trapframe page.
这个 trapframe 页和每个进程都有自己的 trapframe 页。
And, trapframe page actually contains
而且 trapframe 页实际上包含
some interesting bunch of different kinds of data,
一些有趣的不同类型的数据，
but at this point the most important data contains is 32 slots,
但是现在包含的最重要的数据是 32 个插槽，
empty slots in memory in which to save the 32 registers.
内存中用于保存 32 个寄存器的空插槽。
So, the good news right now in the trap handling code is we have a mapping,
所以，现在 trap 处理代码中的好消息是我们有了一个映射，
we're guaranteed to have a mapping set up by the kernel previously
我们保证之前由内核设置了一个映射，
in the user page table that points to a place
在指向某个位置的用户页表中，
where, that's prepared for us to save this processes, user registers.
为我们保存进程、用户寄存器做好了准备。
And it's sure it's three is always 0x3ffffff000 virtual address.
可以肯定的是，它始终是 0x3ffffff000 虚拟地址。
If you want to see what they are actually in that trapframe,
如果你想看看它们在那个 trapframe 里到底是什么，
it's um.
它是，嗯。
What xv6 puts there is defined in, proc.h
xv6 放在那里的内容在 proc.h 中定义，
and struct trapframe which is right here,
trapframe 结构体就在这里，
so you can see, um.
所以你可以看到，嗯。
What's supposed to go in each slot
每个插槽里应该放些什么，
and there's a 32 slots,
这里有 32 个插槽，
you need a ra sp gp whatever which are places to save registers,
你需要 ra sp gp 等用来保存寄存器的位置，
there's also these five things at the beginning,
开头的这五个，
which will see will come in handy very soon,
很快就会派上用场，
which are values that the kernel
这些值是内核预先放置在
previously placed in the slots in the trapframe.
trapframe 的插槽中。
Like, for example this very first slot in the trapframe
例如 trapframe 中的第一个插槽
contains a pointer to the kernel page table,
包含指向内核页表的指针，
and this will be the value that we're very soon going.
这将是我们很快要达到的值。
The trap handling code is going to load into satp.
trap 处理代码将加载到 satp 中。
Okay so, half the answer to how to save the registers is that
好的，那么，如何保存寄存器的部分答案是，
kernel is conveniently mapped this trapframe and every user page table,
内核方便地映射了 trapframe 和每个用户页表，
the other is this instructions, sscratch register which we measured before,
另一个是，这个指令，之前提到过的 sscratch 寄存器，
so there's the specialist sscratch register,
所以有专门的 sscratch 寄存器，
provided by RISC-V for exactly the purpose,
由 RISC-V 提供，
we're about to use it for.
我们将把它用于。
The kernel went before it goes into user space
内核在进入用户空间之前，
puts a pointer there to the trapframe
在那里放置一个指向 trapframe 的指针，
basically just point, puts into satp, this this address
基本上就是指向，放入 satp ，这个地址，
just for the convenience of the trap handling code,
为了方便 trap 处理代码，
more importantly though there's an instruction of the RISC-V
更重要的是，有一个 RISC-V 指令，
that it's going to allow us to swap any register
它允许我们交换任何寄存器，
and that sscratch which will save that register
以及将保存 sscratch 寄存器，
as well as loads value of sscratch into whatever register we specified.
将 sscatch 的值加载到我们指定的任何寄存器中。
As you can see, if I look at the trampoline code.
如你所见，如果我看一下 trampoline 代码。
We're right at the beginning of trampoline code here.
我们现在就在 trampoline 代码的开头。
The very first thing it does is this csrrw
它做的第一件事是 csrrw 指令，
instructions,
说明，
this is the source of this window over this window,
这是源码窗口，
we can actually see what gdb sees in the kernel
我们可以看到 gdb 在内核中看到的内容，
and we've actually just executed this swap instruction.
我们刚刚执行了这个交换指令。
Let's swap a0 with sscratch,
让我们将 a0 和 sscratch 互换，
in order to see what it did, let's print out a0,
为了看看它做了什么，让我们打印出 a0 ，
a0 is now this three f f e zero zero zero value which is a pointer.
a0 现在是这个 0x3fffffe000 值，它是一个指针。
Which is the virtual address of the trapframe
是 trapframe 的虚拟地址，
which used to be in sscratch, but we just swapped it.
它之前在 sscratch 里，我们刚把它交换了。
And then we can print out what's in sscratch,
然后我们可以把 sscratch 中的内容打印出来，
and it's two which is the old value of the a0 register,
它是 2 ，这是 a0 寄存器的旧值，
of course a zero held the first argument to the write function,
当然， a0 保存 write 函数的第一个参数，
just file descriptor to which you put the shell passed,
是 shell 传递到的文件描述符，
so we saved you a0 and we have a pointer to the trapframe.
所以我们保存了 a0 ，并且有一个指向 trapframe 的指针。
And it turns out now that
现在，
we're well on our way to be able to save the registers,
我们可以很好地保存寄存器了，
in fact that's what the very next thirty odd instructions
事实上，这就是 trampoline 代码中
due in this trampoline code
接下来的 30 多条指令，
which is systematically sd instructions,
它是系统的个 sd 指令，
you just save 64 bit store instructions
保存 64 位存储指令，
to store every single register
将每个寄存器
to a different offset in the trapframe a0 to recall,
保存到 trapframe 中 a0 的不同偏移量，
now contains after the swap contains a pointer to the trapframe
现在在交换后包含指向 trapframe 的指针，
that is could change the virtual address of this page.
这可以更改此页面的虚拟地址。
And we're just storing each registered a different offset in the trapframe,
我们只是保存每个寄存器到 trapframe 的不同偏移量，
all the stores a bit boring, so I'm gonna skip over them.
所有的保存有点无聊，所以我跳过它们。
Um. Let me set a break point, go further on.
嗯。让我设定一个中断点，再往前走。
Professor question?
教授，有个问题。
Yes.
好的。
How did the address of the trapframe
当我们用 a0 交换它时，
end up in sscratch when we swapped it with a0.
trapframe 的地址怎么会出现在 sscratch 中呢？
Okay before the kernel, before it previously transitioned to user space,
好的，在内核过渡到用户空间之前，
set sscratch to be equal to 0x3fffffe000, the virtual addresses the trapframe.
将 sscratch 设置为等于 0x3fffffe000 ，这个虚拟地址是 trapframe 。
So all the time when we are executing a user space in the shell,
因此，当我们在 shell 中执行用户空间时，
sscratch had this pointer to the trapframe,
sscratch 具有指向 trapframe 的指针，
and then the shell executes ecall,
然后 shell 执行 ecall ，
which jumps to the beginning of the trampoline
它跳到 trampoline 的起始处，
and the very first instruction of the trampoline,
trampoline 的第一个指令，
is this csrrw instruction which swaps a0 on the sscratch
csrrw 指令交换 a0 和 sscratch ，
and so now the old value of the scratch,
所以现在 sscratch 的旧值，
namely the point of the trapframe is now in a0.
也就是说， trapframe 现在在 a0 。
Does that answer your question.
这回答了你的问题吗。
I guess I'm wondering where in the alloc-,
我想我在想在什么地方，
does this happen during the allocation of the process
在分配进程期间会发生这种情况吗，
like where do the sscratch register live.
比如 sscratch 寄存器在哪里。
Where does this well scratch itself lives on the CPU,
这个 sscratch 寄存器，它本身就在 CPU 上。
the special register in the CPU,
CPU 中的特殊寄存器。
where and the kernel sets it, um well,
内核设置它，嗯，好的，
a little bit involved, the actual place where it's set
有点牵扯进去，就是它设置的实际位置，
and what I'm now showing you on the right here
我现在在右边给你们展示的是
is the code that the kernel,
是内核（执行）的代码，
the last two instructions that the kernel executes while returning a user space,
内核在返回用户空间时执行的最后两条指令，
and what's happening is that the very last thing it does after the kernel
发生的是它在内核之后做的最后一件事，
restores all the user registers
恢复所有用户寄存器，
and it's just about ready to return to user space,
并且准备好返回到用户空间，
it actually does another one of these swaps,
它实际上又进行了一次交换，
the kernel is setup a0 to be equal to the trapframe,
内核设置 a0 为 trapframe ，
sscratch still holds the saved user a0.
sscratch 仍然保存的用户 a0 。
So the kernel does this swap which ends up with that sscratch having a pointer
所以内核会进行这种交换，结果是 sscratch 有一个指针，
that trapframe in a0 having received,
在 a0 中的 trapframe ，
user a0 and then this sret returns to user space,
用户 a0 ，然后 sret 返回到用户空间，
so you may wonder how a0 ever got to have the value
所以你可能会想， a0 怎么会有这样的值，
of the, the address of the trapframe
有 trapframe 的地址，
answer that question is that, um,
回答这个问题是，嗯，
we're now looking in trap.c,
我们现在看 trap.c ，
at this last C function to run
在这最后一个 C 函数中，
on the way out to user space.
它将转移到用户空间。
The last thing this C function does is calls this function here.
这个 C 函数做的最后一件事，是在这里调用这个函数。
Whatever this fn is and the arguments it passes
无论这个 fn 是什么，它传递的参数
are the trapframe and the user page table
都是 trapframe 和用户页表，
and so in C code, when you call a function,
所以在 C 代码中，当你调用一个函数时，
the first argument goes into a0,
第一个参数进入 a0 ，
that's basically why a0 held a pointer at the trapframe.
这就是 a0 在 trapframe 上保持指针的原因。
And this function, its value is set up here to be,
这个函数，它的值在这里设置为，
in that trampoline page towards the end that code I showed you.
在接近末尾的 trampoline 页面中，我向你展示了代码。
This code.
这个代码。
Is that, that's a good answer.
这是不是你要的答案。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Sorry, I also was confused about that I was not sure,
不好意思，我也搞不清楚我不确定，
so when you start when you start your process,
所以当你开始你的过程时，
and it's good at running and then at some point
它运行，然后在某些时候，
it doesn't equal I guess or something
我猜这不等于什么，
and then when did you call this return function
那么在什么时候调用这个返回函数的呢，
because it should have been called before the ecall,
因为它应该在 ecall 之前调用，
but it didn't return from, you didn't return before,
但是它没有回来，你之前没有返回，
I I don't know I don't understand what you call the usertrapret.
我不知道我不明白你说的 usertrapret 。
Okay, what may be one answer to this question is that
好的，这个问题的一个答案可能是，
the kernel always or that the machine boots up in the kernel,
内核总是或机器在内核中引导，
so when the machine starts in the kernel,
因此，当机器在内核中启动时，
anytime the only way to get into user space,
任何时候进入用户空间的唯一途径，
you know the very first time or when returning from a system call
你知道第一次或从系统调用返回时，
is in fact to execute this sret instruction,
实际上是执行这个 sret 指令，
that this sret instruction is the way
这条 sret 指令就是解决问题的方法，
that the RISC-V defines to transition from supervisor mode into user mode,
RISC-V 定义为从管理者模式转换到用户模式，
and so before any user code ever executes,
因此在任何用户代码执行之前，
the kernel executes the code I'm showing you here,
内核执行我在这里展示的代码，
in these these two editor buffers,
在这两个编辑器缓冲区中，
that set up all kinds of things like sscratch stvec.
设置所有内容，比如 sscratch stvec 。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
I have a question,
我有个问题，
I'm not sure if we touched on this or I missed it,
我不确定我们是谈到这个了还是我错过了
but when we call the ecall instruction in the assembly code,
但是当我们在汇编代码中调用 ecall 指令时，
what triggers the trampoline code to start,
是什么触发 trampoline 代码启动，
like is it the switch of the CPU mode from supervisor,
比如 CPU 模式是从管理者模式切换过来的，
I'm sorry from user, supervisor is something else.
对不起，是从用户模式切换过来的吗？管理者模式是另一回事。
Okay, um.
好的，嗯。
So the code we're executing is this ecall,
所以我们正在执行的代码是 ecall ，
the shell executes it in user space
shell 在用户空间中执行它，
and ecall does a couple things,
ecall 做了几件事，
the ecall instruction sets the mode to supervisor,
ecall 指令将模式设置为管理者模式，
and the ecall instruction saves the program counter in sepc
并且 ecall 指令将程序计数器保存在 sepc 中，
and the ecall instruction sets the program counter equal to
并且 ecall 指令将程序计数器设置为等于
the control register called stvec,
名为 stvec 的控制寄存器，
so stvec is one of the many things
stvec 是内核在进入用户空间之前
which the kernel sets up before entering user space.
设置的众多东西之一。
And so here's stvec, stvec is just the kernel set it
这里是 stvec ，内核设置它，
to the beginning of the trampoline page
到 trampoline 页面的开头，
that is this address here.
就是这里的地址。
So when ecall happens,
所以当 ecall 发生时，
ecall just copies stvec into the program counter and continues,
ecall 只是将 stvec 复制到程序计数器中并继续，
but now the program counter is executing this address in the trampoline page.
但是现在程序计数器正在 trampoline 页面中执行这个地址。
That clarifies it, thank you.
清楚了，谢谢。
Okay.
好的。
I also have a question.
我也有一个问题。
Why, so some of the registers are saved in the trapframe,
为什么，所以一些寄存器保存在 trapframe 中，
should not,
是否应该，
are also registers that the user program had access to,
也是用户程序可以访问的寄存器，
why, why do we need to, um, use as a new region in memory
为什么我们要把这个作为内存中的一个新的区域，
and not use the program stack.
而不是使用程序栈。
Okay, um, boy, there's maybe two questions here.
好吧，嗯，伙计，这里可能有两个问题。
One is, maybe why do we have to save the registers at all.
一个是，也许我们为什么要保存这些寄存器。
The the reason why the kernel has to save the registers
内核必须保存寄存器的原因是，
is that the kernel is about to run C code
内核即将运行 C 代码，
that it overwrites those registers
它会覆盖那些寄存器，
and if we ever want to resume the user code correctly,
如果我们想要正确恢复用户代码，
we need to resume it with its registers
我们恢复它需要寄存器
having their original values as of when the ecall,
保持其从 ecall 开始原始值，
let's execute it,
让我们执行它，
we have to save all the registers in the trapframe,
我们必须保存 trapframe 中的所有寄存器，
so that later on, we can restore all of their values
这样以后，我们就可以恢复它们的值，
just before resuming the user code.
在恢复用户代码之前。
Maybe the other half of your question is
也许你问题的另一半是，
how come they're saved in the trapframe
为什么它们保存在 trap 帧中，
and not on the user stack.
而不是保存在用户栈中。
The answer to that is
这个问题的答案是，
that we're not sure the user program even has a stack.
我们甚至不确定用户程序是否有栈。
There are certainly programming languages that don't have a stack
当然，有些编程语言没有栈，
and the stack pointer doesn't point to anything in particular
栈指针没有特别指向任何东西，
might be a value zero,
可能是零值，
there's also programming languages that yeah they have a stack
还有一些编程语言，它们有一个栈，
but it's in a format that's,
但它的格式是，
you know some weird format, the kernel doesn't understand,
一些奇怪的格式，内核无法理解，
maybe because the programming language
可能因为编程语言
allocates stack in small blocks from the heap,
从堆中以小块的形式分配栈，
and the programming language runtime understands
编程语言运行库可以理解，
how to use these small blocks of memory as a stack,
如何将这些小的内存块用作栈，
but you know, the kernel has no idea.
但是你知道，内核并不知道。
So we if we want to be able to run sort of arbitrary
因此，如果我们想要能够任意地运行，
user programs written in lots of different languages
用多种不同语言编写的用户程序，
that kernel can't make any assumptions about what parts of user memory,
内核不能对用户内存的部分做出任何假设，
it's allowed to exist or valid or is allowed to read or write,
它被允许存在或有效，或者被允许读或写，
and so the kernel has to be
因此内核必须
sort of self-contained in saving them, storing the registers.
在某种程度上独立保存它们，保存寄存器。
That's why the kernel saves stuff in its own memory
这就是内核在自己的内存中保存内容的原因，
and the trapframe rather than in user memory.
保存在 trapframe ，而不是在用户内存中。
Okay, makes sense.
好的，有道理。
Okay.
好的。
Anything else.
还有别的问题吗。
Okay, we're still reading the beginning of of the code in trampoline,
好的，我们还在阅读 trampoline 代码的开头。
this code unfortunately we refer to it
这些代码，不幸的是，我们将其称为
both as uservec and as the trampoline code,
uservec 和 trampoline 代码，
we barely started executing it
我们刚刚开始执行它，
I think I just set a break point in this code,
我想我刚刚在这段代码中设置了一个断点，
after all the registers have been saved,
在保存了所有寄存器后，
I think I set a break point of this instruction,
我想我给这个指令设置了一个断点，
we'll continue executing skip over all these saves
我们将继续执行，跳过所有这些保存
of all the user registers the trapframe.
所有用户寄存器的 trapframe 。
Okay and now, we're executing this load instruction,
好的，现在我们执行加载指令，
this load instruction is loading into the stack pointer register
加载指令正在加载到栈指针寄存器，
and what is loading as the value is the eighth slot.
作为值加载的是第八个插槽。
In the block of memory pointed to by a0,
由 a0 指向的内存中的块，
we remember a0 points, this trapframe
我们记得 a0 指向，这个 trapframe ，
to this virtual address the second last page.
到这个虚拟地址的倒数第二页。
And the format of the trap page, but the trapframe.
trap 页面的格式，但 trapframe 。
Here's the front of the trap page,
这是 trap 页的首页，
my we've conveniently labeled each field with its offset in bytes,
我们已经方便地将每个字段以字节为单位标记为其偏移量，
so that means they load in the eighth,
所以这意味着他们在第八个装载，
starting at the eighth byte of the trapframe
从 trapframe 的第八个字节开始，
means we're loading the kernel stack pointer
意味着我们正在加载内核栈指针，
and one of the things the kernel sets up before entering user spaces,
内核在进入用户空间之前设置的事情之一，
it sets this slot in the trapframe
它将 trapframe 中的这个插槽
to be equal to this process's kernel stack,
设置为等于此进程的内核栈，
so this instruction here is doing is initializing the stack pointer
所以这里的这条指令是初始化栈指针，
to point to the top of this process's kernel stack,
指向此进程的内核栈的顶部，
is part of what you need to do in order to to run user code.
是运行用户代码所需执行的操作的一部分。
Alright, so what's left,
好的，那么剩下的，
within a few instructions of getting to the end of the trampoline code.
在到达 trampoline 代码末尾的几条指令。
We loaded the stack pointer,
我们加载了栈指针，
so maybe I can print the stack pointer for you and see.
因此，也许我可以打印栈指针，并查看。
Yeah, this is.
是的，这是。
Um. All right, well this is the kernels,
嗯。好的，这就是内核，
this processes kernel stack is up on high memory
这个进程的内核栈位于高内存上，
because xv6 treat kernel sets especially,
因为 xv6 特别对待内核设置，
so that you can put a guard page under each kernel stack.
这样你就可以在每个内核栈下放置一个保护页。
Um, okay, so this load into tp,
嗯，好的，这个加载到 tp ，
it turns out that because there's no direct way in RISC-V
因为 RISC-V 没有直接的方式，
to figure out what core which of the multiple cores you're running on,
找出你在多个内核中的哪个内核上运行，
xv6 actually keeps the core number called the hart id in the tp register
xv6 实际上将称为 hart id 的内核编号保存在 tp 寄存器中。
and this is used in a bunch of places in the kernel,
这在内核中的很多地方都有使用，
for example, it's part of the machinery
举个例子，它是一种机制，
for kernel code to figure out what process is currently running on that core.
让内核代码找出当前在该内核上运行的进程，
OK, and if we execute this, hopefully,
好的，如果我们执行这个，
tp or running on core zero and that makes sense
tp ，运行在内核 0 上，这是有意义的，
because I've configured QEMU to
因为我已经将 QEMU 设置为
only give one core to xv6 or indeed running on core zero.
仅将一个内核分配给 xv6 或实际上在内核 0 上运行。
Um, this next thing, is loading the address of,
嗯，下一件事是加载地址，
actually the loaded to t0.
实际加载到 t0 。
I think loaded a pointer to the first C function that we're going to execute
我想加载了指向我们要执行的第一个 C 函数的指针，
which is user,
就是 usertrap ，
so we use that in a few instructions
所以我们在几条指令中使用它，
just jump to the usertrap C function.
只需跳到 usertrap C 函数。
Load into t1 here,
加载到 t1 ，
is loading the address of the kernel page table,
正在加载内核页表的地址，
you can print, about to switch page tables,
你可以打印，即将切换页表，
turns out the, this thing,
这个东西，
it was not actually literally the address of the kernel page table,
其实不是字面上的内核页表地址，
it's the thing you need to put into satp,
这是你需要放入 satp 的东西，
which is, has the address of the kernel page table,
即具有内核页表的地址，
but shifted around with some extra flag bit set.
但是对一些额外的标志位的情况下进行了移位。
But as soon as the csrrw instruction executes
但只要执行 csrrw 指令，
will switch page tables from the user page table, the kernel page table,
将交换用户页表和内核页表，
let me just reinforce that by looking at the current page table right now.
现在让我查看当前页表确认一下。
We're still executing with this very small user page table
我们仍在使用这个非常小的用户页表执行，
and run step by to execute the load and satp.
并单步运行以执行加载和 satp 。
Um.
嗯。
And we'll look again at the kernel page,
我们将再次查看内核页面，
now we're at completely different page table right,
现在我们在完全不同的页表中，
this is the kernel page table,
这是内核页表，
then you can see all these different regions of memory
然后你可以看到所有这些不同的内存区域，
and device control registers
和设备控制寄存器，
and what now that the kernel sets up in its own big kernel page table,
现在内核设置在自己的大内核页表中，
so we successfully switch page tables.
所以我们成功地交换了页表。
And now the kernel page tables,
现在是内核页表，
so we're in pretty good shape at this point,
所以现在我们处于相当好的状态，
because we have a stack,
因为我们有栈，
we have the kernel page table,
我们有内核页表，
we can read my kernel data
我们可以读到内核数据
were really pretty much ready to execute C code in the kernel,
已经准备好在内核中执行 C 代码了，
one puzzle though is, how come, we didn't just crash,
但有一个问题是，为什么我们不是崩溃了，
after all we are executing somewhere in memory,
毕竟我们是在内存中的某个地方执行，
and the program counter holds a virtual address,
并且程序计数器保存虚拟地址，
if we switch page tables,
如果我们交换页表，
why doesn't that just cause some random garbage
为什么不会造成一些随机的垃圾数据
or nothing at all to be mapped in the new page table
或者没有东西映射到新页表中，
underfoot where we were executing.
在我们执行之后。
We're not crashing or actually execute these instructions.
我们没有崩溃，也没有实际执行这些指令。
Any guesses what's going on.
有谁能猜到发生了什么事吗？
I think it's because, oh sorry,
我想是因为，哦，对不起，
because we're still in the trampoline code
因为我们还在 trampoline 代码里，
and the trampoline is mapped the same virtual address both user and kernel.
并且 trampoline 被映射到用户和内核的相同虚拟地址。
That's absolutely correct
绝对正确，
and say you, I don't know if you remember
我不知道你是否还记得，
what was mapped here in the user page table,
这里映射的是用户页面表中的内容，
but this mapping here at the end of the kernel page table
但是内核页表末尾的这个映射，
is exactly the same mapping in the same place,
在相同的地方是完全相同的映射，
as as the trampoline mapping
与 trampoline 映射一样，
at the end of the user page table,
在用户页表的末尾，
all the other mappings are different,
所有其他映射都不同，
But this mapping is the same,
但是这个映射是一样的，
this is the mapping that holds the instructions were executing,
这是保存正在执行的指令的映射，
and because it didn't change when we switch page tables,
因为当我们交换页表时它没有改变，
we actually continue executing
我们实际上继续执行，
and we're still executing the same sequence of instructions and not crashing.
我们仍然在执行相同的指令序列，也没有崩溃。
And so that's the sort of special thing about the trampoline page,
这就是 trampoline 页面的特殊之处，
it's mapped both in the user page tables and kernel page table
它在用户页表和内核页表中都有映射，
and the reason it's called a trampoline pages,
这也是被称为 trampoline （蹦床） 页面的原因，
because you sort of bounce on it
因为你可以在上面弹跳，
on the way from user space to kernel space.
从用户空间到内核空间。
And the next instruction, this jr were about to bounce
下一条指令，这个 jr 将要弹跳，
right out of the trampoline into kernel C code.
直接走出 trampoline 进入内核 C 代码。
And see where we're going, jr is just like jump to a subroutine,
看看我们要去哪里， jr 就像跳到一个子程序，
subroutine this point to by register t0,
由寄存器 t0 指向的子程序，
print t0 to see where we're going.
打印 t0 查看我们要去哪里。
Um, maybe we'll print instructions there.
嗯，也许我们在那里打印指令。
Okay, so these are the instructions were about to jump to there
好的，这些就是我们要跳到那里的指令，
in the beginning of the function called usertrap,
在 usertrap 函数的开头，
usertrap is just a C function,
usertrap 只是一个 C 函数，
defined in trap.c.
定义在 trap.c 中。
Here's usertrap, we're about to jump from assembly code to use a trap
这是 usertrap ，我们将从汇编代码跳到使用 trap ，
with a stack with a kernel page table,
利用具有内核页表的栈，
let me actually do the execute the instruction.
让我来执行指令。
And I'm gonna turn on, turn on display of C code
我要打开，打开 C 代码的显示，
and gdb now [] C code.
gdb 现在[] C 代码。
Okay, so now we're in a much more sane world,
好的，现在我们处在一个更加理智的世界里，
we're just executing C code,
我们只是在执行 C 代码，
should be a little bit easier to understand
应该更容易理解一点，
and there's you know still spend some time
还有你知道的，仍然要花一些时间
reading and writing various interesting control registers,
读写各种有趣的控制寄存器，
but the environment is hopefully a good deal
但是，环境更好，
less mysterious than it was in the trapframe.
比在 trap 帧的神秘程度要低得多。
Alright.
好的。
Any function, any any questions at this point.
对于这一点，有什么问题吗。
Um, I have a question,
嗯，我有个问题，
why didn't we see with the gdb, what ecall does,
为什么我们没有在 gdb 看到 ecall 是做什么的，
I I maybe I missed it,
也许我错过了，
but I I think we've jumped directly into the trampoline.
但是我想我们已经直接跳到 trampoline 上了。
Ecall ecall did jump, what ecall does is,
ecall 确实跳了， ecall 做的是，
just switch just changes the mode bit to be supervisor
只需切换，将模式位更改为管理员模式，
and ecall sets the program counter register to be equal to
而 ecall 设置程序计数器寄存器等于，
the whatever happens, whatever the kernel happened to store in stvec.
无论内核发生什么，存储在 stvec 中的值。
I'll store this value I just printed 0x3ffffff000
我将存储刚刚打印的值 0x3ffffff000 ，
which is the beginning of the trampoline page kernel stores.
这是 trampoline 页面内核存储的开始。
This number in stvec before entering user space,
在进入用户空间之前在 stvec 中的编号，
so where eccall goes that is where it's just the program counter to stvec,
因此， ecall 所处的位置就是 stvec 的程序计数器。
which is the beginning of the trampoline page.
这是 trampoline 页面的开始。
That answer your question.
这回答了你的问题吗。
Yes I think so.
是的，我想是的。
Okay, so now we're in user, usertrap are actually just like a trampoline page
好的，现在我们在 usertrap ， usertrap 就像一个 trampoline 页面，
and just like the trampoline page for a number of different kinds of traps,
就像 trampoline 页面上为一些不同种类的 trap ，
there system calls there's exceptions like dividing by zero
有系统调用异常，比如被零除，
or using a unmapped virtual address
或使用未映射的虚拟地址，
and there's a device interrupts
或有设备中断，
and they all come here
它们都来到这里
and so user sort of saves and restores some hardware state,
因此 usertrap 可以保存和恢复一些硬件状态，
but it also needs to look at the state at the cause of the trap
但它也需要查看引起 trap 的状态，
to figure out what to do with it.
弄清楚如何处理它。
And so we're gonna see both things as we execute along in usertrap,
所以当我们在用户陷阱中执行时，我们会看到这两种情况，
let me just run stuff user,
让我运行一下 usertrap ，
let's see, the first thing it does here is that
让我们看看，它在这里做的第一件事是，
it changes that stvec register,
它改变 stvec 寄存器，
it turns out that the the way xv6 handles traps is different
xv6 处理 trap 的方式不同，
depending on whether they come from user space or from the kernel
取决于它们是来自用户空间还是来自内核，
and we've only been talking about what happens if a trap occurs from user space,
我们只讨论了如果用户空间发生 trap 会发生什么，
there's a quite different sequence of events,
事件的顺序完全不同，
for traps that come from the kernel that occur while in the kernel,
对于内核中发生的，来自内核的 trap ，
because after all, for example the kernel,
因为毕竟，比如说内核，
I was already using the kernel page table,
我已经在使用内核页表了，
a trap occurs while you're in the kernel,
当你在内核中发生 trap ，
you already have the kernel page tables,
你已经有了内核页表，
there's a whole bunch of stuff that doesn't have to happen
有很多事情是不一定要发生，
if the trap occurred while in the kernel,
如果 trap 在内核中发生，
so before getting much further in the kernel code,
所以在深入了解内核代码之前，
we change stvec to point to this kernelvec
我们将 stvec 更改为指向 kernelvec ，
which is the kernel trap handler,
它是内核 trap 处理程序，
rather than the user trap handler.
而不是用户 trap 处理程序。
We need for various reasons,
出于各种原因，我们需要，
we need to figure out what process we're running
我们需要找出我们正在运行的进程，
and we do that by calling this myproc function
我们通过调用这个 myproc 函数来实现这一点，
and myproc actually looks at an array
并且 myproc 实际上查看一个列表，
indexed by the current core number, hart id,
由当前内核编号， hart id ，
do you remember we put in tp.
你记得我们把它放入 tp 。
Um, that's how myproc figures out what process is currently running.
嗯，这就是 myproc 计算出当前正在运行的进程的过程。
We need to save that save
我们需要保存，
user program counter is still sitting there in in sepc,
用户程序计数器还在 sepc 中，
but because one of things that could happen while we're in the kernel is
但是因为当我们在内核中时可能发生的一件事是，
that we might switch to another process
我们可能会切换到另一个进程，
and that other process might go into that process user space
而另一个进程可能进入该进程用户空间，
and that other process might make a system call,
而另一个进程可能会进行系统调用，
which causes sepc to be overwritten,
这使得 sepc 被重写，
we have to save our sepc and some memories associated with this process,
我们必须保存 sepc 和与此过程相关的一些内存，
so it doesn't get overwritten
这样它就不会被覆盖，
and yet we use this trapframe to save epc
我们用这个 trapframe 来保存 epc ，
as well as lots of other stuff,
还有很多其他的东西，
anyway that's with this current line of code is doing.
不管怎样，这就是当前代码行正在做的事情。
The next thing happens,
接下来的事情，
we need to figure out, why we came here,
我们需要弄清楚我们为什么来这里，
the scause, the RISC-V scause register
scause RISC-V 的 scause 寄存器，
has a different number depending on why this trap occurred.
根据 trap 发生的原因，具有不同的数字。
Some kind of exception versus system call versus device interrupt,
某种异常或系统调用或设备中断，
value eight means we're here we took a trap because of a system call.
8 表示我们因为系统调用而进入 trap 。
Indeed scause eight it does have eight were here because a system call,
事实上， scause 8 ，它在这是 8 就是因为系统调用，
so we're gonna execute this statement.
所以我们将执行这条语句。
First thing is if some other process is killed this process,
第一件事是，如果某个其他进程杀死这个进程，
we don't want to continue but that's not the case for shell.
我们不想继续，但 shell 并非如此。
It turns out that the RISC-V the program counter that gets stored in sepc
RISC-V 程序计数器保存在 spec ，
is the address of the instruction that caused the trap,
是引起 trap 的指令的地址，
but when we resume we want to resume at the next instruction after the ecall,
但是当我们恢复时，我们想要恢复 ecall 之后的下一条指令，
so therefore we this code persistent calls which need to return.
因此，这个代码持久化需要返回的调用。
We add four to the saved user program counter,
我们将保存的用户程序计数器加 4 ，
so that we resume in the next instruction
这样我们就可以在下一条指令中继续，
and don't just re-execute the ecall.
而不要重新执行 ecall 。
Alright next, turns out that xv6 enables interrupts
好的，接下来， xv6 启用中断，
while handling system calls just that interrupts
在处理系统调用时，只有中断
can be served faster some system calls take a lot of time.
可以更快地提供服务，某些系统调用需要很长时间。
Interrupts are always turned off by the RISC-V trap hardware,
中断始终由 RISC-V trap 硬件关闭，
and so we have to explicitly turn them back on at this point.
因此我们必须在这里显式地重新打开它们。
And the next thing that happens is we call this syscall function,
接下来发生的是，我们调用这个 syscall 函数，
the job of syscall just entering defined in just syscall.c.
syscall 是在 syscall.c 中定义的。
Here we are what it does, is it looks up the syscall number
这就是它所做的，它查找 syscall 编号，
in this big table of system calls about at the top of the page,
在页面顶部的这个系统调用表中，
if you remember the shells write function
如果你还记得 shell write 函数，
set register a7 to the system call number namely sixteen for write,
将寄存器 a7 设置为系统调用号 16 进行写入，
so what syscall does is it retrieves the saved a7
所以 syscall 的作用是获取保存的 a7 ，
that was saved away in the trapframe by the trampoline code,
被 trampoline 代码保存在 trapframe 里，
and use that to index into this table of pointers to functions
并使用它来索引此指向函数的指针表，
that implement each system call.
这些函数实现了每个系统调用。
So we're gonna [] this number gonna print num now,
所以我们现在要[]这个数字， print num ，
that's the saved a seven indeed sixteen
这就是保存在 a7 中的，实际上是 16 ，
the same sixteen the shell originally put there.
和 shell 原来放在那里的 16 一样。
Um.
嗯。
The system call code indexes indices calls table,
系统调用代码索引调用表，
we can find out what function can,
我们可以找出哪些函数可以，
it got out of the system call table,
它是从系统调用表中取出的，
by stepping into it,
通过单步进入，
right now we're in write or SYS_write.
现在我们在 write ，或 SYS_write 。
So, in this sysfile.c,
所以，在 sysfile.c 文件中，
sys_write is the kernel implementation of the write system call.
sys_write 是 write 系统调用的内核实现。
I'm not gonna go into this, it's like fairly complicated,
我就不详细说了，这里很复杂，
what happens from here out and in
从外面和里面会发生什么，
and the implementation of this system call
而且这个系统调用的实现，
for this lecture,
对于本课程，
I'm only really interested in getting into and out of the kernel,
我只对进出内核感兴趣，
so I'm going to step over,
所以我要跳过，
the actual implementation system call.
实际的系统调用实现。
One thing an interesting thing to note is
有一件有趣的事情需要注意，
that the system calls need to find their arguments
系统调用需要找到它们的参数，
so you remember the arguments to write
你还记得 write 的参数，
or to add a buff pointer and another two,
一个 buff 指针还有其他两个，
and the way that the system call code gets at them
系统调用代码获取它们的方式，
is just looking at these,
就是查看这些，
well, looking at the trapframe,
好的，查看这个 trapframe ，
so just like we could look in the trapframe for a7,
就像我们可以在 trapframe 中查找 a7 ，
we can look for a0 and that's the first argument,
我们可以查找 a0 ，这是第一个参数，
we look at a1, that's that buff pointer,
我们查看 a1 ，这就是 buff 指针，
we can look at a2 that's the second argument,
我们可以查看 a2 ，这是第二个参数，
the number of bytes to write.
也就是要写入的字节数。
Okay, so the system call does its job
好的，那么系统调用就完成它的工作，
and then a sys_write finally returns.
然后，最终 sys_write 返回。
And watch what happens,
看看会发生什么，
the reason for this assignment here,
这个分配的原因是，
the reason why we're assigning to a0 in the trapframe is
我们将 trapframe 中的 a0 赋值的原因是，
that this system calls all have a return value.
这个系统调用都有返回值。
Like write returns, the number of bytes written,
比如 write 返回，写入的字节数，
and the convention and for C code on the RISC-V
约定，并针对 RISC-V 上的 C 代码，
is that return values are placed in register a0
将返回值放入寄存器 a0 ，
by whatever function you're calling
通过你正在调用的任何函数，
and so to simulate a return value,
因此，要模拟返回值，
we just stick the return value in a0 in the trapframe
我们只需将返回值放入 trapframe 中的 a0 中，
and we'll see by and by that when we return to user space,
当我们回到用户空间时，我们会看到它，
this a0 slot in the trapframe is restored back into the actually a zero register
trapframe 中的 a0 插槽恢复到真正的 a0 寄存器，
and the shell sees that a0 value as as the return value from write
并且 shell 将 a0 的值看作从 write 返回的值，
and execute through this and print p trapframe a0,
并通过这个执行，print p->trapframe->a0 ，
we'll see the value to what that means is that write return values too,
我们也会看到值，也就是 write 的返回值，
saying that it actually wrote two bytes just as instructed.
表示它实际上是按照指令写了两个字节。
Okay, at this point, we're back in trap.c
好的，现在我们又回到了 trap.c ，
and usertrap just after the call to syscall,
usertrap 紧接在对 syscall 调用之后，
for now with this p
现在，使用这个 p ，
which checking if the func if the process been killed,
它检查进程是否已终止，
because you don't want to resume executing have already been killed,
因为你不想恢复已经被终止的进程，
of course, our shell not been killed.
当然，我们的 shell 没有终止。
Skip over this and then,
跳过这个然后，
usertrap calls a separate function usertrapret
usertrap 调用单独的函数 usertrapret ，
in order to set up all the stuff that I talked about previously
为了设置我之前谈到的所有东西，
whenever I said well before entering user space,
每当我在进入用户空间之前，
the kernel does blah blah,
内核做这个那个，
it's usertrapret,
usertrapret ，
that's responsible for setting all that stuff up.
负责设置所有这些东西。
And so we can look at all the different things, it does,
所以我们可以看到所有不同的东西，它做，
it turns interrupts off
它关闭中断，
and when they were turned on for the duration of a system call
并且当它们在系统调用期间被打开，
were turned off now,
现在被关闭，
because we're about to change the stvec
因为我们即将修改 stvec
to point to the user trap handler,
指向用户 trap 处理程序，
whereas while we're in the kernel was pointing to the kernel trap handler,
而当我们在内核时，指向内核 trap 处理程序，
so we turn off interrupts,
所以我们关闭了中断，
because once we changed stvec to point to the user trap handler,
因为一旦我们将 stvec 更改为指向用户 trap 处理程序，
we're still executing in the kernel,
我们仍然在内核中执行，
and if an interruption occur then we go to the user trap handler,
如果中断发生，则我们转到用户 trap 处理程序，
even though we're executing in the kernel
即使我们在内核中执行，
and for various detailed reasons, that would cause the kernel to malfunction.
由于各种原因，会导致内核故障。
So we turn off interrupts and their left off from between the time.
因此，我们关闭中断，并在这两个时间之间保持关闭。
From the very next line where we set up the stvec
从我们设置 stvec 的下一行开始，
to point to the trampoline all the way through the final sret instruction
在最后的 sret 指令中指向 trampoline ，
that returns to user space.
返回到用户空间。
It turns out that sret instruction at the end of the trampoline,
trampoline 最后的 sret 指令，
turns interrupts back on.
重新打开中断。
So the interrupts are on when we're executing in a user code,
所以当我们在用户代码中执行时，中断是开启的，
even though we just turn them off.
即使我们刚把它们关掉。
The next couple of lines, fill in those trapframe slots that we saw before
接下来的几行，填充我们之前看到的 trapframe 插槽，
that hold various values that are convenient for the trampoline code.
包含对 trampoline 代码方便的各种值。
So, the code here, stash away a pointer
所以，这里的代码，存放一个指针
to the kernel page table in the trapframe,
到 trapframe 中的内核页表，
its stash away a pointer to this processes, kernel stack,
它存放指向此进程、内核栈指针，
Stashed away in the trapframe.
存放在 trapframe 里。
A pointer to the usertrap function,
指向 usertrap 函数的指针，
which is what the trampoline code jump to at the very end.
这是 trampoline 代码最后跳转的地方。
Stash away, the current core number,
存放当前的内核编号，
read from the tp register,
从 tp 寄存器读取，
so that the trampoline code can just restore that same value,
使得 trampoline 代码可以恢复相同的值，
because user code may have disturbed it.
因为用户代码可能会干扰它。
Question?
有一个问题。
Yes.
是。
Why didn't we save the sepc in the trampoline?
我们为什么不把 sepc 保存到 trampoline ？
It could have.
可以这样。
Yeah that that the sepc could have been trampoline code happens
是的， sepc 可以保存在 trampoline ，
not to save it along with other registers,
而不是将其与其他寄存器一起保存，
we perfectly well could modify the xv6 to save it,
我们完全可以修改 xv6 来保存它，
where it is actually saves you.
它为你保存的。
Probably remember is, just happened to save it
可能记得是，只是碰巧保存了一下，
and usertrap and C code instead of an assembly code, in the trampoline code.
以及 usertrap 和 C 代码，而不是汇编代码，在 trampoline 代码中。
I don't think, I can't think of a good reason to do it one way or the other.
我不认为，我想不出一个好的理由来做这件事。
The user registers really have to be saved in the assembly code.
用户寄存器确实需要在在汇编代码中保存。
Because any C code is entitled for all we know the compiler generates code
因为据我所知，任何 C 代码都是由编译器生成代码，
which modifies any user registers,
修改任何用户寄存器，
those user registers are pretty important to save them
保存这些用户寄存器很重要，
in assembly code before entering C.
在汇编代码中，在进入 C 代码之前。
But the sepc we could have saved earlier or later.
但是我们可以早点或晚点保存 sepc 。
Okay, so when usertrapret sort of preparing the trap,
好的，所以当 usertrapret 准备 trap 时，
we prepared the trapframe with all these values
我们准备了 trapframe ，
that are going to be needed next time.
其中包含下次需要的所有这些值。
There's a transition from user space to kernel next trap.
有一个从用户空间到内核 trap 的转换。
There's a couple things we have set up in the sstatus control register,
我们在 sstatus 控制寄存器中设置了几项内容，
it turns out this spp bit in sstatus,
结果是 sstatus 中的这个 spp 位，
controls whether controls the mode that sret return,
控制 sret 返回的模式，
by clearing it we're just saying look next time you execute sret,
通过清除它，我们是说下次执行 sret 时，
we want to go to user mode instead of supervisor mode
我们希望进入用户模式，而不是管理者模式，
and this spie bit controls whether interrupts will be enabled,
这个 spie 位控制是否启用中断，
after we execute sret and then after we get into user space,
在我们执行 sret 之后，然后进入用户空间，
and we do want them to be enabled.
我们确实希望它们能够启用。
So, gonna set that spie bit
所以，我要设置 spie 位，
and I'm going to write this new modified status
我将把这个新的修改状态
into the actual hardware status register.
写入实际硬件状态寄存器。
It turns out what sret does.
它证明了 sret 是做什么的。
You know the sret we're gonna execute write at the end of the trampoline code,
你知道我们要执行的 trampoline 代码末尾的 sret ，
what that sret does is,
sret 做的是，
sets the program counter equal to the sepc register,
将程序计数器设置为等于 sepc 寄存器，
so we're now going to set up the sepc register
所以我们现在要设置 sepc 寄存器，
to have the saved user program counter.
以保存用户程序计数器。
Which, if you recall we recently saved the trapframe,
如果你记得我们最近保存了 trapframe ，
that's what's happening here.
这就是这里正在发生的事情。
You remember also the trapframe contain a pointer to a kernel page table
你还记得 trapframe 包含指向内核页表的指针，
because the trampoline needs to switch to it,
因为 trampoline 需要转换成这个，
we need to cook up the special bit pattern
我们需要准备出特殊的位模式，
that you need to write to satp has done here.
你需要写入 satp 的操作已在此完成。
And.
而且。
I'm sorry, we're now preparing a pointer to the user page table.
很抱歉，我们现在正在准备一个指向用户页表的指针。
Which we need to switch to on the way into user space.
我们需要在进入用户空间的过程中切换到它。
We're actually going to do that switch in assembly code,
我们实际上要在汇编代码中进行切换，
because it has to happen in the trampoline,
因为它必须在 trampoline 上进行，
because only code in the trampoline is mapped in both user and kernel space,
因为只有 trampoline 中的代码在用户空间和内核空间中都被映射，
so we can only really switch page tables,
所以我们只能真正交换页表，
we're executing on the trampoline,
我们在 trampoline 上执行，
but we're not executing on the trampoline yet,
但我们还没有在 trampoline 上执行，
we're still just in an ordinary C function,
我们仍然只是在一个普通的 C 函数中，
so we prepared this pointer
所以我们准备了这个指针，
and we're going to pass it to the assembly code as the second argument in a1.
我们将把它作为 a1 中的第二个参数传递给汇编代码。
With this line here doing is just calculating the address
这里的这一行所做的就是计算地址，
of where we want to jump to at the end of the trampoline code
我们想要跳到 trampoline 代码末尾的地方，
and it turns out there's a, that we want to go with userret
这里有一个，我们要用 userret ，
user, that's the address of the instructions
这是将我们
that will take us back to user space
带回用户空间的指令地址，
and this little formula works out,
这个小公式计算出，
the address the virtual address in the trampoline
trampoline 中虚拟地址
that corresponds to that userret function.
对应于 userret 函数。
Oops.
哎呀。
Okay, so we calculate the address of that.
好的，我们来计算一下它的地址。
userret function, and then this mess, this next line,
userret 函数，然后这个乱七八糟的，这个下一行，
call uses this fn variable as a function pointer
调用使用 fn 变量作为函数指针，
and jumps to that function with these two arguments in a0 a1.
并跳转到 a0 a1 中带有这两个参数的函数。
And we can now just go to trampoline code.
现在我们可以直接去 trampoline 代码了。
The trampoline code, there's.
trampoline 代码，有。
Well first we switch to the user page tables,
好的，首先我们切换到用户页表，
I mean actually execute this
我的意思是，实际上执行这个命令，
and we can see the page tables change,
我们可以看到页表发生了变化，
just for [], we're still using the giant kernel page table.
作为验证，我们仍然使用大的内核页表。
Um.
嗯。
I'm gonna run through usertrapret quickly
我将快速浏览 usertrapret ，
until we get to the point where it jumps to the trampoline.
直到我们到了它跳到 trampoline 。
Oh.
噢。
Alright we're in the trampoline.
好的，我们在 trampoline 了。
These instructions are about to start
这些指令即将
executing the trampoline code there right here,
在这里开始执行 trampoline 代码，
we can now, again, printed page table
我们现在可以，再次，打印页表，
is still the kernel page table.
仍然是内核页表。
The first thing that's gonna happen here though is
不过，这里要发生的第一件事是，
that the trampoline code is going to load the,
trampoline 代码将会加载，
that pointer to the user page table into the satp register.
指向用户页表的指针到 satp 寄存器。
So we switch page tables, I typed info mem now,
所以我们现在交换页表，我输入 info mem ，
we now have a much smaller user page table,
我们现在有一个小得多的用户页表，
but luckily still with the trampoline page map,
但幸运的是还有 trampoline 页面映射，
so we don't crash on the next instruction.
这样我们就不会在下一条指令上崩溃。
The next thing happens, is this a.
接下来会发生什么，是。
The I showed you a while ago,
刚才我给大家看的，
the second last thing that this sequence of code does
这段代码的第二件最后一件事是
on the way to user spaces swaps sscratch with a zero,
在跳入用户空间时交换 sscratch 和 a0 ，
so we need to setup sscratch,
所以我们需要设置 sscratch ，
it's saved user a0,
它是保存的用户 a0 ，
so that when we do that swap,
所以当我们交换的时候，
a0 will end up having received user a0,
a0 具有接收到的用户 a0 ，
turns out a0 pointer to the trapframe,
最终 a0 指向 trapframe ，
because the C code pass that is the first argument,
因为 C 代码传递的是第一个参数，
one twelve a0 is the address of the saved a0
112(a0) 是保存的 a0 的地址，
in the trapframe going to load that.
在要加载的 trapframe 中。
And then into t0 and then load that into sscratch.
然后放入 t0 ，然后将其加载到 sscratch 。
At this point, we're still running with kernel stuff and all the registers.
此时，我们仍在运行内核内容和所有寄存器。
The next 32 instructions, though load out of the trapframe
接下来的 32 条指令，是从 trapframe 加载出来，
which is a0 points to load all of the saved user registers
a0 将所有保存的用户寄存器
out of the trapframe into the actual registers,
从 trapframe 加载到实际寄存器中，
were really close to being able to the point where we can run user code,
已经接近能够运行用户代码，
I'm going to skip over all these loads.
我将跳过所有这些加载。
Any questions before we approach closer to user space.
在我们接近用户空间之前，有什么问题吗。
And one quick question,
有一个简短的问题，
is the value in the trapframe a zero,
trapframe a0 中的值，
now the return value of that system call that we made.
现在是我们进行的那个系统调用的返回值吗？
Um.
嗯。
Yeah yeah, the really a zero holds this point of the trapframe,
是的，现在 a0 控制着 tramframe ，
but the after we execute the,
但是在我们执行完之后，
well s, OK the current location of the user's saved,
好的，用户保存的当前位置，
yes I was calling at the user saved a0
是的，我在调用用户保存的 a0 ，
but in fact the system call returns stuff overrode it,
但实际上系统调用返回的内容会覆盖它，
with the return value that we want the shell to see in a0,
使用我们希望 shell 在 a0 中看到的返回值，
so the current location of that a0 which we overwrote with two.
所以我们用 2 覆盖了 a0 的当前位置。
As the return value is sscratch appoints sscratch
因为返回值为 sscatch ，
and hope that it's equal to two,
希望它等于2，
it is equal to two.
它等于 2 。
Does that answer your question?
这回答了你的问题吗？
Yes I think so.
是的，我想是的。
Okay.
好的。
I'm gonna skip over all these loads restore,
我会跳过所有这些加载恢复，
to save user values out of the trapframe into the registers,
为了将用户值从 trapframe 保存到寄存器中，
I'm going to print out the registers at this point.
我现在要打印寄存器。
Um, actually gonna.
嗯，实际上。
Print the registers I don't know if these look familiar,
打印寄存器，我不知道这些看起来是不是很眼熟，
but they happen to be the same set of user registers,
但是它们是同一组用户寄存器，
you saw way back at the beginning of this exercise,
你在这个练习开始的时候就看到了，
for example a1 or the stack pointer holds this small value
例如 a1 或栈指针在存储器中保持这个值，
appropriate for user stack low in memory,
在内存中适合于用户栈的小值，
a1 is that buff pointer that we passed write
a1 是我们向 write 传递的缓冲区指针，
two is that number of bytes,
2 是字节数，
a0, however is the exception is not received user value,
然而， a0 是个例外，不是接收到的用户值，
because it still has the pointer to trapframe in it.
因为它仍然有指向 trapframe 的指针。
But let's look we're about to execute,
让我们看看我们即将执行的，
rather execute is this csrrw a0 sscratch,
要执行的 csrrw a0 sscratch ，
right at the end of trampoline just before returning to user space
就在 trampoline 的尽头，在返回用户空间之前，
is going to swap a0 and scratch,
将交换 a0 和 sscratch ，
scratch indeed has.
scratch 包含。
Um, that's sscratch.
嗯，是这个 sscratch 。
As two which is going to be the return value a0 as this kernel pointer,
2 是关于该内核指针的返回值 a0 ，
and it points to, point to the trapframe,
它指向 trapframe ，
but after executing the csrrw instruction to swap them,
但是在执行 csrrw 指令交换它们之后，
hopefully we'll see that a0 holds this return value of two,
我们能看到 a0 包含这个返回值 2 ，
and sscratch holds a pointer to the trapframe
而 sscratch 保存指向 trapframe 的指针，
which is the second last page in memory,
这是内存中倒数第二页，
and that value is going to stay in sscratch
该值将保留在 sscratch ，
until the user program does another trap
直到用户程序执行另一个 trap ，
and at that point, the trap handling code, we talked about before,
那时 trap 控制代码，我们之前讨论的，
we'll be able to use sscratch at the trapframe.
我们能在 trapframe 使用 sscratch 。
Alright, we're still in the kernel,
好的，我们还在内核中，
that is our last instruction in the kernel,
这是我们在内核中的最后一条指令，
and when I execute this sret,
当我执行这个 sret 时，
it will switch to user mode,
它将切换到用户模式，
before I do that let's look at.
在我这样做之前，让我们先来看看。
It'll switch user mode, it'll copy sepc to PC,
它将切换用户模式，将 sepc 复制到 pc ，
because we're still, we're still executing with the pc that's in the trampoline,
因为我们还在用 trampoline 上的 pc 执行任务，
so sret gonna switch the user mode copy sepc to pc.
因此， sret 将切换用户模式，复制 sepc 到 pc 。
And then resume executing, so I'm gonna run the sret.
然后继续执行，所以我将运行 sret 。
Boom, I'm now we're back at.
砰，我们现在又回到原点了。
I could address 0xdea which is a low address
我可以寻址 0xdea ，它是一个低地址，
likely be user memory, and it's the.
很可能是用户内存，它是。
Look back in sh.asm and address 0xdea.
回顾 sh.asm 和地址 0xdea 。
Is indeed the address of the return function at the end of write.
实际上是 write 结束时返回函数的地址。
And, a0 is this return value, they're supposed to be returning.
a0 是这个它们应该返回的返回值。
So we're back in user space
所以我们回到了用户空间，
and we can about to do the return back to the shell from the write system,
我们可以执行从 write 系统返回到 shell 的操作，
from the write library function that made the system call.
从进行系统调用的 write 库函数。
OK, any questions?
好的，有什么问题吗？
Um, sorry, can you repeat again,
嗯，不好意思，你能再重复一遍吗，
what happens with the interrupt during sret.
在 sret 期间中断发生了什么。
What happened with interrupts.
中断之后发生了什么。
You, you say we are turning them off,
你说我们把它们关了，
but then something else turns them back on.
然后又有别的东西把它们打开了。
sret, sret re-enables interrupts,
sret ， sret 重新启用中断，
so this sret, the very last instruction
所以 sret ，最后一条指令，
that we're executing in supervisor mode in the kernel,
我们在内核中以管理者模式执行的，
I forgot to say that just now,
刚才我忘了说，
but as well as setting the program counter equal to the sepc
但也将程序计数器设置为等于 sepc ，
and switching to user mode sret is going to re-enable interrupts.
切换到用户模式 sret 将重新启用中断。
So that means you know that's you know
这意味着你知道，
user programs may run for a long time,
用户程序可能会运行很长时间，
it would be nice to be able to take disk interrupts or whatever,
能够接受磁盘中断或其他任何情况很好，
while user programs are running.
当用户程序正在运行时。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢你。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay.
好的。
Okay to, to wrap up the system calls,
好的，总结一下系统调用，
sort of look like function calls
看起来有点像函数调用，
and are kind of meant to be thought of a lot like function calls,
它们在某种程度上被认为很像函数调用，
but the user kernel transitions are much more complex than than function calls
但是用户内核转换比函数调用要复杂得多，
are a lot of complexities due to the requirement for isolation,
由于隔离的要求有很大的复杂性，
the kernel just can't trust anything in user space.
内核就不能信任用户空间中的任何东西。
And also the desire to have simple and very fast hardware mechanisms,
并且还希望具有简单且非常快速的硬件机制，
really xv6 doesn't care that much about performance,
xv6 不太关心性能，
but in general operating system designers and the CPU designers,
但是在一般的操作系统设计者和 CPU 设计者中，
they're very interested in
他们非常感兴趣的是
the sort of speed at which you can do efficiency of traps.
你能以多快的速度，以及 trap 的效率。
xv6 does it does all these things in a particular way,
xv6 以一种特殊的方式做所有这些事情，
there's certainly other ways to do them,
当然还有其他方法可以做到这一点，
a few questions if you design questions alternatives,
几个问题如果你设计问题替代方案，
you could think about,
你可以想一想，
one is can you think of ways to make the hardware or software aspects,
一个就是你能不能想办法把硬件方面或者软件方面，
you redesign xv6, redesign the RISC-V to make this whole sequence simpler
你重新设计 xv6 ，重新设计 RISC-V 以使整个序列更简单，
or could you think of ways to make the whole sequence faster.
或者你能想出让整个过程更快的方法吗？
Another sort of set of questions to keep the back your head,
另一组问题让你保持头脑清醒，
is whether or not a malicious programs
恶意程序是否可以
could abuse any of these mechanisms to break isolation.
滥用这些机制中的任何一个来破坏隔离。
Alright that is all I have to say for this lecture.
好了，这就是我对这堂课要说的全部内容。
I'm happy to take questions.
我很乐意回答大家的问题。
Um, sorry I have another question.
嗯，对不起，我还有另一个问题。
Please.
请问。
I saw there is a uie registers are,
我看到有一个 uie 寄存器，
yeah I think register in sstatus,
是的，我想它在 sstatus ，
but we don't use it,
但是我们不使用它，
we just use, sie and we set it to false in user space,
我们只使用 sie ，并在用户空间中将其设置为 false ，
why couldn't we use the uie.
为什么我们不使用 uie 。
Uie gosh, the answer is gonna be I don't know.
uie ，天啊，答案是我不知道。
Um.
嗯。
We're s p what we said is s, what we said is spie.
我们 s p ，我们说的是 spie 。
We may actually end up setting.
我们实际上可能最终会设置。
Um I know nothing about uie, I'm gonna guess,
嗯，我对 uie 一无所知，我只能猜一下，
let me see, I'm gonna guess that what actually happens here.
让我想想，我要猜猜这里到底发生了什么。
In this code where we're.
在此代码中，我们所在的位置。
Um, OK, so here we are in usertrapret
嗯，好的，那么我们现在在 usertrapret ，
returning or setting spie sstatus
返回或设置 spie sstatus ，
and I believe the sret instruction will copy this spie
我相信 sret 指令会复制这个 spie ，
and this is this previous name of this,
这是这个以前的名字，
the supervisor previous interrupt enable,
管理者以前终端开启（spie），
I suspect sret copies that bit into the,
我怀疑 sret 将该位复制到，
into whatever controls interrupts and user mode,
复制到任何控制中断和用户模式，
which is possibly the uie, bit of sstatus,
这可能是 uie ， sstatus 的一个位，
as that for guess.
这就是我的猜想。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢你。